<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life of Mr. Thomas Firmin, late citizen of London written by one of his most intimate acquaintance ; with a sermon on Luke X. 36, 37 preach'd on the occasion of his death ; together with An account of his religion, and of the present state of the Unitarian controversy.</title>
            <author>One of his most intimate acquaintance.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52614</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4561</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13081195</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13081195</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97235</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52614)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97235)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 747:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life of Mr. Thomas Firmin, late citizen of London written by one of his most intimate acquaintance ; with a sermon on Luke X. 36, 37 preach'd on the occasion of his death ; together with An account of his religion, and of the present state of the Unitarian controversy.</title>
                  <author>One of his most intimate acquaintance.</author>
                  <author>Nye, Stephen, 1648?-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-118, 83 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and sold by A. Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Stephen Nye. Cf. McAlpin Coll.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: "A sermon on Luke X. 36, 37" and "An account of Mr. Firmin's religion, and of the present state of the Unitarian controversy" lacking on filmed copy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Firmin, Thomas, 1632-1697.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97235:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97235:1"/>
            <p>THE LIFE OF Mr. <hi>THOMAS FIRMIN,</hi> Late Citizen of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by one of his moſt intimate Acquaintance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH A SERMON On <hi>Luke</hi> x. 36, 37.</p>
            <p>Preach'd on the occaſion of his Death.</p>
            <p>Together with an Account of his RELIGION, and of the preſent State of the <hi>Unitarian Controverſy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and ſold by <hi>A. Baldwin</hi> in <hi>Warwicklane.</hi> MDCXCVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97235:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97235:2"/>
            <head>THE LIFE OF Mr. <hi>THOMAS FIRMIN.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE long Acquaintance, and intimate Friendſhip, I had with Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> are (I confeſs) warrantable Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that ſo many do expect from me, an account of his (memorable) Life. If ſome other man would anſwer the publick expectation, with more Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs; as to Expreſſion, Method, num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and value of Obſervations and Reflec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; in a word, more Ambitiouſly: yet I will not be wanting in Sincerity, or Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Firmin</hi> was born at <hi>Ipſwich</hi> in <hi>Suffolk;</hi> in the month of <hi>June, Anno</hi> 1632. being the Son of <hi>Henry Firmin,</hi> and of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97235:3"/>
               <hi>Prudence</hi> his Wife. <hi>Henry</hi> and <hi>Prudence,</hi> as they did not overflow with wealth of the World; ſo neither was their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Low, or Strait. God gave them, the wiſh of <hi>Solomon, neither Poverty nor Riches;</hi> but that middle Eſtate and Rank, which containeth all that is valuable and deſirable in Wealth, without the Gaude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Vanity and Temptations, that (ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally) adhere to Riches. But theſe two were very conſiderable in their degree, or place, both as to eſteem, and plenty; by means of their Sobriety, Diligence, and good Conduct, the <hi>effects</hi> of their Piety. They were of the number of thoſe, who were then called <hi>Puritans,</hi> by the looſer ſort of people: who were wont to impute Preciſianiſm, or affected Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, to ſuch as were more Devout; and withal, more Conſcientious, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary, than is ordinary; tho in the way of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When he was of capable years for it, they put their Son <hi>(Thomas Firmin)</hi> to an Apprentiſhip in <hi>London;</hi> under a Maſter who was (by Sect or Opinion) an <hi>Arminian,</hi> a Hearer of Mr. <hi>John Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyn.</hi> Our young man, accompanying his Maſter to the elegant and learned Sermons of Mr. <hi>Goodwyn,</hi> ſoon exchanged the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97235:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>(harſh) Opinions of <hi>Calvin,</hi> in which he had been educated; for thoſe (more Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to God, and more accountable to the Human Reaſon) of <hi>Arminius</hi> and the Remonſtrants. And now it was, that he learned, as was the commendable Cuſtom of thoſe times, to write Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand; at which he was ſo dextrous, that he would take into a Book, any Sermon that he heard, word for word as it was ſpoke by the Preacher; if the Sermon were not delivered, with too much pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitance. Of this he made a double uſe; both then, and <hi>in the very buſieſt part of his Life.</hi> For, if the Sermon was conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, for (judicious) Morality, or weighty Arguments; he often read it, in his Short-hand Notes, for his own further Improvement: <hi>and</hi> then took the pains, to write it out (in words at length) for the benefit of his Acquaintance. He left behind him a great many little Books of that kind; Sermons, copied fair from his Short-hand notes: which, not ſeldom, are <hi>multum in parvo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to his demeanor, in his Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; he was ſo nimble in his motions, in taking down, opening Goods to Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that ſome gave him, the name of Spirit. And in making his Bargain, his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97235:4"/>Words and Addreſs were ſo pleaſing, and reſpectful; that after ſome time, the Cuſtomers rather choſe to deal with <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> than with the Maſter of the Shop: or if a Bargain ſtuck between a Cuſtomer and his Maſter, he would decide the difference to the liking of both.</p>
            <p>He met however with one rub, in the courſe of his Service; for the elder Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice interverted five pounds of his Maſters money, and laid it to the charge of <hi>Tom Firmin.</hi> I know not whether the Imputation was believed, probably it was not; but it pleaſed God himſelf to judg in the caſe. For the elder Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant was, ſhortly after, taken with a mortal Sickneſs; and before he died made confeſſion, that he took and ſpent his Maſters mony, <hi>Tho. Firmin</hi> not being in the leaſt privy to it. Thus he that made all things, the very leaſt, does not diſdain or neglect to judg all things, even little things, in the propereſt time. Many Crimes are ſuffered to reſt, or are not <hi>preſently</hi> called to judgment; becauſe the delay of Juſtice ordinarily hurts no body: but when the Innocent and Virtuous lie under imputations, by occaſion of the guilt of others; the detection of Offenders, and the execution of wrath is but ſeldom (if ever) reſpited.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97235:4"/>
            <p>So ſoon as he was made free, he began to trade for himſelf, tho his firſt Stock was but about 100 <hi>l.</hi> By the opinion he had raiſed of himſelf among the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and others, and the love he had gained among his Maſter's Cuſtomers, the Neighbourhood, and a great number of incidental Acquaintance, he overcame the difficulties of ſo weak and incompetent a beginning; ſo that in the year 1660 he married a Citizens Daughter with 500 <hi>l.</hi> Portion.</p>
            <p>From his firſt ſetting up (as they ſpeak) for himſelf, he would be acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all perſons that ſeemed to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, Foreigners as well as Engliſh, more eſpecially Miniſters: he ſeldom dined without ſome ſuch at his Table; which, tho ſomewhat chargeable to his (then) ſlender abilities, was of great uſe to him afterwards, both in relation to the Poor, and the Publick. For out of his large Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quanitance and multitude of Friends, he engaged the (powerful) Intereſt of ſome, and the (weighty) Purſes of others; in ſome of thoſe great deſigns of Charity, or other Services to the Publick, for which I ſhall hereafter account.</p>
            <p>Now alſo it was, that he hapned on Mr. <hi>Bidle,</hi> who much confirmed him in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97235:5"/>his <hi>Arminian</hi> Tenents, and carried him a great deal further. Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> perſwaded him, <hi>that</hi> the Unity of God is a Unity of <hi>Perſon</hi> as well as of <hi>Nature; that</hi> the Holy Spirit is indeed a <hi>Perſon,</hi> but not <hi>God.</hi> He had a great and juſt eſteem of Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi>'s Piety, Exemplarineſs and Learning; and is that Friend (mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi>'s Life) who gave Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> his Bed and Board till he was ſent Priſoner by Protector <hi>Oliv. Cromwel</hi> to the Iſle of <hi>Scilly;</hi> and when there, Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> with another Friend, procured for him a yearly Penſion of 100 Crowns from the Protector, beſides what he obtained from other Friends, or gave himſelf.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s <hi>Diverſion,</hi> in this part of his Life, was Gardening; for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he cultivated a piece of ground at <hi>Hoxton,</hi> not a mile from <hi>London;</hi> where he raiſed Flowers, and (in time) at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained no ſmall skill in the art of Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dening, in the culture of Flowers, Herbs, Greens, and Fruit-trees of all ſorts. I have often born him company to his Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; but either going or coming back he uſed often to viſit the Poor and Sick: this was one of Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi>'s Leſſons, that 'tis a duty not only to relieve, but <hi>to viſit</hi> the Sick and Poor; becauſe they are hereby
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97235:5"/>encouraged and comforted, and we come to know of what nature and degree their ſtraits are; and that ſome are more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of aſſiſtance than others: and their condition being known, ſometimes we are able to aſſiſt them by our Counſel, or our Intereſt, much more effectually than by the Charity we <hi>do</hi> or <hi>can</hi> beſtow upon them.</p>
            <p>Before I paſs to the next Scene of Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Life, I am obliged to take notice, that by his firſt Wife he had a Son and a Daughter; the former lived to man's eſtate, but died (a Batchelor) about ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years before his Father. The Mother of theſe two Children died while Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was (occaſionally) at <hi>Cambridg,</hi> managing there ſome affairs of his Trade: her death was accompanied with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Circumſtance. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> dreamt at <hi>Cambridg,</hi> that he ſaw his Wife breathing her laſt: whereupon early in the morning he took Horſe for <hi>London;</hi> but on the way thither he met the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger who was ſent to give him notice of her deceaſe.</p>
            <p>Another (neceſſary) Remark belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this part of his Life is, that tho hitherto his wealth was no more than a <hi>competence,</hi> conſidering his liberal humour,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97235:6"/>and the multitude of his Acquaintance; yet he was even then a moſt kind Brother, Uncle and Kinſman: Of which the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may take account in this following Tranſcript, being the Copy of a Paper written by one of his neareſt Relations, and who hath lived with him above thirty years, and was (a great part of that time) his Partner; being a Perſon of great Sobriety, Diligence, Integrity and Prudence. <q>He had many Relations, of ſeveral degrees, who ſtood in need of his care and help; to whom he was a very kind Brother, Uncle and Kinſman: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the great pains he took to promote them, as it lay in his way or power: his loſs by ſome of them, for whom he advanced money, and his disburſments for others of them, amounted to very conſiderable ſums; a good part of which was not long after his firſt beginning in the World; which was the greater prejudice to him, becauſe <hi>then</hi> his own circumſtances required mony to carry on his Trade with eaſe and advantage. Be ſure he had then more occaſion for his mony, than when he was arrived to a very conſiderable Eſtate, which he did not till about ſeventeen years before his death. His Eſtate at (about) ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97235:6"/>years before his deceaſe, was <hi>three times greater than when he died,</hi> tho then conſiderable. He might eaſily have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed it as much as he diminiſhed it, had he ſet his heart on Riches; but thoſe he never valued in compariſon of doing good: and I have often heard him ſay, <hi>he would not die worth more than Five Thouſand Pound.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Of his Liberalities to the Poor, and the Deſerving, and the <hi>motives</hi> to them, I may ſay enough hereafter. But for his beneficence to his Kindred, it proceeded not <hi>merely</hi> from the benignity of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or natural Affection; which (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) to cheriſh and improve is a great virtue; but from his <hi>reverence to the Chriſtian Religion.</hi> For as he would fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſay, that Paſſage of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> is to be read as it ſtands in <hi>the Margin</hi> of our Bibles, <q>He that provides not for his own KINDRED, is worſe than an Infidel:</q> ſo he was wont to give that Text as <hi>the reaſon of his Bounties to his Relations.</hi> So far was he from that <hi>Deiſm,</hi> of which ſome have been ſo over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward to ſuſpect him.</p>
            <p>During the Impriſonment of Mr. <hi>Bidle</hi> at <hi>Scilly,</hi> Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was ſetled in <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardſtreet,</hi> where firſt Mr. <hi>Jacomb,</hi> then
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97235:7"/>Dr. <hi>Outram,</hi> was Miniſter: With theſe two, being excellent Preachers, and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, he maintained a reſpectful and kind Friendſhip; which was anſwered as affectionately and cordially on their parts. Now alſo he grew into intimacy with Dr. <hi>Whichcot,</hi> Dr. <hi>Worthington,</hi> Dr. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tillotſon:</hi> Dr. <hi>Wilkins</hi> was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> (for he was not yet made Doctor) Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> but in their Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and to the very laſt, Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> had the ſame place and degree in their eſteem and friendſhip, that at any time formerly he had. While Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> preached the <hi>Tueſdays</hi> Lecture at St. <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> ſo much frequented by all the Divines of the Town, and by a great many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality and Diſtinction: when the Doctor was obliged to be at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> where he was Dean, or was out of Town, either for diverſion or health; he generally left it to Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> to provide Preachers for his Lecture, and Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> never fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſupply his place with ſome very eminent Preacher; ſo that there never was any complaint on the account of Dr. <hi>Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotſon</hi>'s abſence. And this Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> could eaſily do, for <hi>now</hi> there was hardly a Divine of Note, (whether in <hi>London,</hi> or in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97235:7"/>the Country that frequented <hi>London</hi>) but Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was come acquainted with him. Which thing helped him much to ſerve the Intereſts of many (hopeful) young Preachers and Scholars; Candidates for Lectures, Schools, Cures, or Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; for whom he would ſolicit with as much affection and diligence as other men do for their Sons, or near Relations.</p>
            <p>See here a Trader, who knew no Latin or Greek, no Logick or Philoſophy; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt about by an incredible number of learned Friends, who differed ſo widely in opinion from him, and were continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally attacking him for his (ſuppoſed) Errors; yet could they never remove him from the belief of <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of God,</hi> nor did <hi>their</hi> Importunities, or his Reſiſtance, break off (or ſo much as leſſen) the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip between 'em; certain arguments of the extraordinary wit and good addreſs of our Friend.</p>
            <p>Her late Majeſty (Queen <hi>Mary</hi>) of moſt happy memory, having heard much of Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s uſefulneſs in all publick Deſigns, eſpecially thoſe of Charity; and that he was heterodox in the Articles of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, the Divinity of our Saviour, and the Satisfaction; She ſpoke to Archbiſhop <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> and earneſtly recommended it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97235:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>to him, to ſet Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> right in thoſe weighty and neceſſary points. The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop anſwered, that he had often en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd it; but Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> having ſo early and long imbibed the <hi>Socinian</hi> Doctrine, was not now capable of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary impreſſion. However his <hi>Grace</hi> publiſhed his Sermons (formerly preached at St. <hi>Lawrence</hi>'s) concerning thoſe Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſent Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> one of the firſt Copies from the Preſs. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> not convinced by his <hi>Grace's</hi> Reaſonings, or his Arguments from Holy Scripture, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a reſpectful Anſwer (altho ſome have ſtretched one Expreſſion too far) entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Conſiderations on the Explications and Defences of the Doctrine of the Trinity,</hi> to be drawn up and publiſht, himſelf giving to his <hi>Grace</hi> a Copy of it. I muſt not omit to do the Archbiſhop right againſt thoſe who pretend, that the Archbiſhop, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thoſe Sermons, was in his heart a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian.</hi> For Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf told me, ſhortly after the Archbiſhop had publiſht thoſe Sermons, that going to <hi>Lambeth,</hi> and the Archbiſhop hapning to dine in private, he ſent for Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> to him, and ſaid to this effect, That the Calumnies of people had obliged him to publiſh his Sermons, ſome time ſince
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97235:8"/>preached at St. <hi>Laurence</hi>'s againſt the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents of <hi>Socinus;</hi> that he had ſincerely preached, as he <hi>then thought, and continued ſtill to think of thoſe Points;</hi> that however no bodies falſe imputations ſhould provoke him to give ill Language to perſons who diſſented <hi>conſcientiouſly,</hi> and for <hi>weighty reaſons.</hi> That he knew well this was the caſe of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> for whoſe learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and dexterity he ſhould always have a reſpect, as well as for their ſincerity and exemplarineſs. Afterwards, when Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> gave him a Copy of <hi>the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations;</hi> after he had read it, he only ſaid, <hi>My Lord of</hi> Sarum <hi>ſhall humble your Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> Nor did he afterwards at any time expreſs the leaſt coldneſs on the account of the Anſwer made to him, but uſed Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> as formerly, enquiring as he was wonted, <hi>How does my Son</hi> Giles? ſo he called Mr. <hi>Firmins</hi> Son by his ſecond Wife.</p>
            <p>About the time the (Great and Good) Archbiſhop died, the Controverſie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Trinity and the depending Queſtions, received an unexpected Turn. The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> took notice from <hi>D. Peta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius,</hi> Dr. <hi>R. Cudworth, S. Curcellaeus,</hi> the <hi>Oxford</hi> Heads, Dr. <hi>S—th</hi> and others, that their Oppoſers agreed indeed in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for a Trinity of Divine Perſons,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97235:9"/>but differed <hi>from one another, even as much as from the</hi> Unitarians, concerning what is to be meant by the term <hi>Perſons.</hi> Some of'em ſay, three Divine <hi>Perſons</hi> are three (Eternal Infinite) <hi>Minds, Spirits, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> and <hi>Beings;</hi> but others reject this as Hereſie, Blaſphemy, and Tritheiſm. Theſe <hi>latter</hi> affirm, that GOD is <hi>one</hi> (Infinite, Eternal, All-perfect) <hi>Mind and Spirit;</hi> and the Trinity of <hi>Perſons</hi> is the Godhead, Divine Eſſence, or Divine Subſtance, conſidered as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbegotten, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, and Proceeding:</hi> which <hi>Modes</hi> or <hi>Properties</hi> they (further) explain by <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Wiſdom,</hi> Unbegotten, and therefore named the Father; the <hi>reflex Wiſdom,</hi> Logos, or WORD, which being gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated or begotten, is called the Son; and the eternal Spiration of <hi>Divine Love,</hi> that has therefore the name of <hi>Holy Spirit.</hi> The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> never intended to oppoſe any other Trinity, but a Trinity of (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite) <hi>Minds</hi> or <hi>Spirits;</hi> grant to 'em, that GOD is one Infinite Spirit or Mind, not two or three, they demand no more. They applied themſelves therefore to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, which of theſe Trinities, a Trinity of <hi>Spirits</hi> or of <hi>Properties,</hi> is the Doctrine of the Catholic Church: they could not miſs of a ready ſatisfaction; all Syſtems,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97235:9"/>Catechiſms, Books of Controverſie, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, Writers that have been eſteemed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic, more eſpecially ſince the (Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral) <hi>Lateran Council, Anno</hi> 1215. and the Reformation, have defined GOD to be <hi>one Infinite All-perfect Spirit;</hi> and the Divine <hi>Perſons</hi> to be nothing elſe but the Divine Eſſence or <hi>Godhead,</hi> with the three <hi>relative Properties,</hi> Unbegotten, and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, and Proceeding. They ſaw there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore plainly, that the difference between the Church and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> had aroſe from a meer miſtake of one anothers meaning: a miſtake occaſioned (chiefly) by the unſcriptural terms <hi>Trinity, Perſons,</hi> and ſuch like. They reſolved, that it became them, as good <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to ſeek the Peace of the Catholic Church, and not to litigate about <hi>Terms,</hi> (tho never ſo <hi>unproper,</hi> or implying only <hi>Trifles</hi>) when the <hi>things</hi> intended by thoſe Terms, are not unſound or heterodox. Theſe (Honeſt, Pacific) Inclinations of men, who drove no deſign in their diſſent from the Church, gave birth to <hi>the Agreement between the</hi> Unitarians <hi>and the Catholic Church;</hi> a Book written at the inſtance (chiefly) of Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> in Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> the Biſhops of <hi>Worceſter, Sarum</hi> and <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> and Monſieur <hi>de
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97235:10"/>Luzanzy.</hi> I need not to ſay, what will be owned by every (Ingenuous) Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Perſon, without heſitance, that <hi>the Agreement</hi> is as well the Doctrine of the Catholic Church, as of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians;</hi> and that in <hi>all</hi> the points, ſo long and fiercely debated and controverted by the Writers of this and of former Ages. It muſt be confeſt, the hands of a great many excellent Perſons did concur to this Re-union of Parties that ſeemed ſo wide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unreconcilably divided, and did encourage the Author of <hi>the Agreement</hi> in his (diſintereſſed laborious) ſearches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Antiquity, and other parts of Learning; and ſeveral learned men, ſome of them Authors in the <hi>Socinian</hi> (or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian</hi>) way, examined the Work with the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and Ingenuity, that is as neceſſary in ſuch caſes, as Learning or Judgment are. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> publiſht it when examined and corrected, with more ſatisfaction than he had before given forth ſo many Eriſtic Writings. I did not wonder how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, that our Friend was ſo ready to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a reconciliation with the Church: for he was ever a lover of Peace, and always <hi>conformed as far as he could,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that direction of the Apoſtle, <hi>Whereunto we have already attained, let us
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97235:10"/>walk by the ſame Rule.</hi> Which with the beſt Interpreters he underſtood thus, <q>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Doctrines, Terms and Uſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that are commonly received, as far as you can; if in ſome things you dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the Church, yet agree with her, and walk by <hi>her Rule</hi> to the utmoſt that in Conſcience you may; or as the Apoſtle himſelf words it, <hi>ſo far as</hi> (or whereunto) <hi>you have attained.</hi>
               </q> From this Principle it was, that our Friend ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver approved of thoſe who ſeparate from the communion of the Church on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Ceremonies, Habits, form of Government, or other <hi>mere Circumſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi> of Religion. He was wont to tell ſuch, that <hi>ſeeing</hi> 'twas undeniable, they might communicate with the Church <hi>without either ſin or ſcandal,</hi> and did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate on ſome occaſions; it <hi>is</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both ſcandal and ſin to ſeparate and divide. With this he ſilenced many, and reclaimed divers.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1658. the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> were baniſht out of <hi>Poland,</hi> the occaſion this; <hi>Poland</hi> had been long haraſs'd with moſt dangerous Civil, and Foreign Wars, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that at one time there were in Arms in <hi>Poland, Lithuania</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>krain,</hi> One hundred and fourſcore thouſand <hi>Poles,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97235:11"/>as many <hi>Tartars,</hi> and two hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Coſſacks,</hi> beſides powerful Bodies of <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> and <hi>Tranſilvanians,</hi> which at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacked <hi>Poland</hi> on the <hi>Weſt</hi> and <hi>South.</hi> The ravages and deſolations committed, and cauſed ſo by many great Armies in a Country that has but few fortified Places, were unexpreſſible: <hi>Poland</hi> therefore was reduced to ſuch a feeble and deſperate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that their King himſelf withdrew; and the King of <hi>Swedes</hi> took the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their confuſion and low eſtate, to invade them with Forty thouſand men, regular Troops. He took the Cities of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw</hi> and <hi>Cracow,</hi> and with them almoſt all <hi>Poland:</hi> he conſtrained the <hi>Polanders</hi> to take an Oath of Subjection and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to him; which Oath was firſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto, and taken by the Roman-Catholies, then by the Proteſtants, and not till laſt of all by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians.</hi> But the <hi>Swediſh</hi> King engaging himſelf in other Wars, particularly with <hi>Denmark,</hi> and in <hi>Germany, John Caſimire,</hi> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> appeared again; and the <hi>Poles</hi> generally joining their King, at length drove the <hi>Swedes</hi> out of <hi>Poland:</hi> the <hi>Swediſh</hi> King found himſelf obliged to condeſcend to a (reaſonable) Peace with King <hi>Caſimire.</hi> As the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> were the laſt that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97235:11"/>to the obedience of <hi>Swedeland,</hi> ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bound thereto by an Oath, they did not concur with the other <hi>Polanders</hi> in rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt him: they conſiered the <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> King as a fair Conqueror, and a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Prince, and themſelves as tied to him by Oath; therefore they even oppoſed in ſome places, the revolt from him. This was interpreted a deſertion of their natural Prince, and native Country; and (tho all the Part-takers with the <hi>Swediſh</hi> King were included in the Peace made with him) was avenged in the very next Diet after the Peace, by a Decree and Edict, the ſum of which was as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows. <q>The Toleration granted by the Laws, and Coronation-Oaths of the Kings to Diſſenters from the Church, does not legally extend to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> (whom they called <hi>Arians,</hi> or <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi>) this being a new Hereſie, ſince the granting that Indulgence or Toleration; therefore all <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> who within ſuch a limited time, will not embrace the Roman-Catholic Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſhall be baniſht out of <hi>Poland,</hi> allowing however two years (in effect but one) to ſell their Eſtates, whether real or perſonal.</q> Hereupon the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians</hi> left <hi>Poland,</hi> and ſetled ſome in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97235:12"/>
               <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> where divers Provinces and Cities are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian;</hi> ſome in <hi>Ducal Pruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> and <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> where they enjoy like Privileges with his Electoral High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes other Subjects; ſome (few) in <hi>Holland.</hi> Theſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> were (in my opinion) unhappy, that they had not a man among them, who could diſcern it, and ſhew 'em, that neither in the Article of the Trinity, nor of the Divinity of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, they had any <hi>real</hi> difference with the Catholic Church: and that the Terms uſed by the Church, imply nothing that is contrary to the Unity of God, as 'tis held by the learned men. Their Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they publiſht upon their Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, aſcribes as much to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, as is intended by the <hi>Catholic-terms</hi> Incarnation, God-man, God the Son, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatical (or perſonal) Union, and the reſt: therefore ſeeing the Church will not diſmiſs thoſe (unſcriptural) Terms, but (for certain reaſons) contents her ſelf to interpret them to a ſound ſenſe, it had been well if the <hi>Poliſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> had been ſo dextrous, as to diſtinguiſh between an unſound Senſe, and improper Terms; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming only the former, and ſubmitting to the latter. The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian</hi> Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>Poland</hi> had many poor perſons,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97235:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>therefore the Nobility and Gentry prayed a Contribution for them, from all <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Churches of foreign parts: and tho they knew there were but few <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian</hi> Families in <hi>England,</hi> they ſent a Letter to us to entreat our help. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured for 'em ſome aſſiſtances from private perſons: and tho without a Brief, ſome collections in Churches; both theſe in the Year 1662. But I mention this for the ſake of what hapned <hi>Anno</hi> 1681. for then King <hi>Charles</hi> granted a Brief for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of <hi>Polonian</hi> Sufferers, Proteſtants alſo: theſe were they who had ſuffered the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> to be baniſht about twenty years before, when it was in their power to have prevented it, if ſo much as one of their Deputies had proteſted againſt it in the Diet. They willingly permitted, nay they promoted the Violation of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Diſſenters not twenty years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and now weakned by the loſs of the whole <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian</hi> Intereſt, it came to their own turns to be the Sufferers: they had never loſt either Country, or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, if they had not voted themſelves out of both, by their (former) Votes againſt the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians.</hi> A Toleration or Liberty of Religion, once tapped, will ſoon run all out; for break it but in one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97235:13"/>or Party, and you have diſannulled the whole <hi>Reaſon</hi> of it, and all the <hi>Pleas</hi> for it. The malice of any whomſoever againſt the <hi>Engliſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> comes now too late; they leſs diſſent from the Church (if they are at all Diſſenters) than any other denomination of Diſſenters: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let thoſe Diſſenters look to it, who have promoted a Bill, in name and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, againſt Immorality, and <hi>Blaſphemy;</hi> in truth and real deſign againſt the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians.</hi> I ſaid King <hi>Charles</hi> granted a Brief for the <hi>Polonian</hi> Proteſtants, who had aſſiſted in baniſhing the <hi>Polonian <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians;</hi> this Brief Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> promoted as much as in him lay: I find he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of Nine Diſſenting Congregations, 110 <hi>l.</hi> 16 <hi>s.</hi> 10 <hi>d.</hi> And in another Book I find the ſum of 568 <hi>l.</hi> 16 <hi>s.</hi> o ¾. col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected on the ſame account.</p>
            <p>We are now come to another part of Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Life, his ſecond Marriage: in the Year 1664. he married to a Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a Juſtice of Peace in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and had with her, beſides all the qualifications of a good Wife, a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Portion. God was pleaſed to lend to 'em ſeveral Children; but one Son, <hi>Giles Firmin,</hi> lived to man's eſtate. He was
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97235:13"/>like to be an eminent Merchant, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther giving him the whole Portion he had received with his Mother: and the young Gentleman going into <hi>Portugal,</hi> to manage there his own buſineſs; he was called by the Heavenly Father to Eternal Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1665. was a great Plague, of which there died in that one year, in <hi>London</hi> only, near One hundred thouſand perſons: moſt of the wealthier Citizens removed themſelves and Children into the Country; ſo did Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> but left a Kinſman in his Houſe, with order to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſome Poor weekly, and to give out Stuff to employ them in making ſuch Commodities as they were wont. He foreſaw that he ſhould be hard put to it, to diſpoſe of ſuch an abundance of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities as theſe poor people would work off, in ſo long time, for him only: but when he returned to <hi>London,</hi> a wealthy Chapman (who was greatly pleaſed with his adventurous Charity) bought an extraordinary quantity of thoſe Goods; ſo that he incurred no loſs, at that time, by employing the Poor.</p>
            <p>The year after the Sickneſs came the Fire, by which the City of <hi>London</hi> ſuſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the damage of Ten millions of Pounds
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97235:14"/>ſterling. Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> with his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, ſuffered the loſs of his Houſe in <hi>Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> and took (thereupon) a Houſe and Warehouſe in <hi>Leaden-hall-ſtreet.</hi> But now his fine Spirit, and generous way of Trading were ſo well known, that in a few years he ſo improved his Stock, that he rebuilt his Houſe, and built alſo the whole Court (excepting two or three Houſes) in which he lived. And having now provided ſufficiently for himſelf and Family, he began to conſider the Poor.</p>
            <p>His firſt ſervice to them, or rather to God in their perſons, was the building a Warehouſe by the Water-ſide, for the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up Corn and Coals, to be ſold to the Poor in ſcarce and dear times at moderate and reaſonable rates, at the rates they had been purchaſed, allowing only for loſs (if any ſhould happen) by damage of the Goods while kept.</p>
            <p>He went on with his Trade in <hi>Lombard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet</hi> till the Year 1676. at which time I eſtimate he was worth about Nine thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds. If we conſider, that this Eſtate was raiſed from a beginning of about One hundred Pounds, in an ordinary way of Trade, and in about twenty years time; to what a mighty wealth would it
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97235:14"/>have grown, in the hands of ſuch a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nager, in his remaining twenty or one and twenty years? Had not his ingenit Liberality, great Mind and Zeal of ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Divine Majeſty, turned his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours a contrary way; to ſupport, and to raiſe others, while he leſſened and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired himſelf. For this year he erected his Warehouſe in <hi>Little Britain</hi> for the imployment of the Poor in the Linen Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture. Let us hear what Archbiſhop <hi>Tillotſon</hi> (then but Dean <hi>Tillotſon</hi>) ſays of this Deſign of Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> in his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Sermon on Mr. <hi>Gouge, Anno</hi> 1681. <q>He (Mr. <hi>Gouge</hi>) ſet the Poor of St. <hi>Sepulchres</hi> Pariſh (where he was Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter) to work, at his own charge. He bought Flax and Hemp for them to ſpin; when ſpun, he paid them for their Work, and cauſed it to be wrought into Cloth, which he ſold as he could, himſelf bearing the whole loſs. This was a very wiſe and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choſen way of Charity; and in the good effect of it a much greater Charity, than if he had given to thoſe very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (freely and for nothing) ſo much as he made them to earn by their work: becauſe by this means he reſcued 'em from two moſt dangerous Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97235:15"/>Idleneſs and Poverty. This courſe ſo happily deviſed, and begun by Mr. <hi>Gouge,</hi> gave, it may be, the firſt hint to that uſeful and worthy Citizen, Mr. <hi>Tho. Firmin,</hi> of a much larger Deſign; which has been managed by him, ſome years in this City, with that vigour and good ſucceſs, that <hi>many hundreds of poor</hi> Children, and others who lived idle before, unprofitable both to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and the Public, now maintain themſelves, and are alſo ſome advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the Community. <hi>By the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and Charity of many</hi> excellent and well-diſpoſed perſons, Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to bear the unavoidable loſs and charge of ſo vaſt an Undertaking; and by his own forward inclination to Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and unwearied diligence and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, is fitted to ſuſtain, and go through the incredible pains of it. <bibl>
                     <hi>Serm. on Mr.</hi> Gouge, <hi>p.</hi> 62, 63, 64.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis of this Project and Warehouſe, that Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> himſelf ſpeaks in a Book of his, entituled, <hi>Propoſals for the employment of the Poor,</hi> in theſe words: <q>'Tis now above four years ſince I ſet up my Workhouſe in <hi>Little Britain,</hi> for the imployment of the Poor, in the Linen Manufacture; which hath afforded ſo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97235:15"/>great help and Relief to <hi>many hundreds of poor</hi> Families; that I never did, and I fear never ſhall do an Action more to my own ſatisfaction, or to the good and benefit of the Poor.</q> He employed in this Manufacture, ſome times 1600, ſome times 1700 Spinners, beſides Dreſſers of Flax, Weavers and others.</p>
            <p>Becauſe he found that his Poor muſt work ſixteen hours in the day to earn ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and thought that their neceſſities and labour were not ſufficiently ſupplied or recompenſed by thoſe earnings; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was wont to diſtribute Charity among them, as he ſaw their need, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> and in hard weather. Without which Charity, ſome of them had periſhed for want, when either they or their Children fell ill. He uſed alſo to lay in vaſt quantities of Coals, which he gave out by a Peck at a time: who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of the Spinners brought in two pound of Yarn, might take away with 'em a Peck of Coals, beſides what Coals were given to ſuch as were antient, had many Children, or any ſick in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. But becauſe they ſoiled themſelves by carrying away Coals in their Aprons or Skirts; to obviate that inconvenience, and damage to 'em, he gave 'em Canvaſs
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97235:16"/>Bags. Cleanlineſs contributing much to health, he diſtributed among 'em Shifting made of the coarſer and ſtronger ſort of Cloth, that had been ſpun by themſelves, and of the ſame among their Children. Much of this Shifting he begged for them; for he found among his Acquaintance and Friends, divers charitable perſons, who would rather buy the Cloth that had been wrought by our Home-Poor, than purchaſe it, tho at ſomewhat cheaper rates, from Merchants or Shops, that ſell ſcarce any but foreign Cloth. By the aſſiſtance and order of his Friends, he gave to Men, Women and Children, ſometime 3000 Shirts and Shifts in two years. But ſtill further to encourage and help his Poor, he would invite perſons of Ability to come to his Workhouſe, on days the Spinners brought their Yarn; that ſeeing their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and Diligence, he might the more eaſily perſuade 'em to give, or ſubſcribe ſomething for their relief. Some would work, but knew not the art of Spinning, or were not able to purchaſe Wheels and Reels; for theſe he hired Teachers, and freely gave 'em their Reels and Wheels: He often took up poor Children as they were begging in the Streets, whom he cauſed to be taught at his own charge,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97235:16"/>and provided for 'em their Reels and Wheels, which were never deducted out of their Work.</p>
            <p>In his Book of <hi>Propoſals</hi> he takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that <q>In above 4000 <hi>l.</hi> laid out the laſt Year, reckning Houſe-rent, Servants wages, Loſs by Learners, with the Intereſt of the Mony, there was not above 200 <hi>l.</hi> loſt. One chief reaſon of which, was the Kindneſs of ſeveral Perſons; who took off good Quantities of Commodities, at the Price they coſt me to ſpin and weave: And in particular, the <hi>Eaſt-India</hi> and <hi>Guinea</hi> Companies gave me Encouragement, to make their <hi>Allabas</hi> Cloths, and coarſe Canvas for Pepper Bags; which before they bought from foreign Countries.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He publiſhed that Book of <hi>Propoſals,</hi> to engage others, to ſet the Poor on work, at a Publick Charge; or at leaſt to aſſiſt him, and two or three Friends, in what he had now carried on, for above Five Years, at the loſs of above <hi>One Thouſand Pounds.</hi> But finding that my Lord Mayor, and the Aldermen, were not perſuaded by what he had offered in his Book, and by Diſcourſe with them, and other Wealthy Citizens; he began to leſſen the Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Trade: For I find that in the Year
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97235:17"/>1682, the whole Disburſment was only 2337 <hi>l.</hi> 3 <hi>s.</hi> and yet the Loſs thereby that Year, was 214 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſhould ſeem he met not ſo many Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Perſons, who would buy his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture at the Price it coſt him, as in ſome former Years: Nay from this time, the Loſs increaſed yearly upon him: For ſeven or eight Years together he loſt two Pence in the Shilling, by all the Work of his Poor; but he was content, for he would ſay, <hi>Two Pence given them by Loſs in their Work, was twice ſo much ſaved to the Publick, in that it took them off from Beggary, or Theft.</hi> But his Loſs ſome Years was extraordinary. In the Year 83. the Trade encreaſing again, his own Disburſments, beſide his Friends, were not leſs than 2000 <hi>l.</hi> the Loſs for that Year was 400 <hi>l.</hi> Continuing thus, in the Year 84. the Balance of Loſs not then received, amounted to 763 <hi>l.</hi> And in the Year 85. it encreaſed to 900:11:3. toward which Loſs, an eminent Citizen, who had 500 <hi>l.</hi> in that Stock, quitted the whole Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, and required no Intereſt. In the Years 86, 87, 88, and 89, the Trade de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined for want of more ſuch Benefactors. The Loſs now remaining being 413:11:3. the value of the Goods then in hand, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97235:17"/>Debts ſtanding out, computed at 372 <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>s.</hi> 1. <hi>d.</hi> I find of the whole no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd than 279:0:1. which falling ſhort 93:3:0. added to the former Loſs of 413:11:3. makes 506:14:3. This whole Sum I find not any way made good, but ſtands ſtill as due to Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> tho' never reckon'd by him as any part of his Eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1690. The Deſign was taken up by <hi>the Patentees of the Linen Manufacture;</hi> who made the Poor and others, whom they employed, to work cheaper; yet, that was not ſufficient, to encourage them to continue the Manufacture. The <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentees</hi> agreed with Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> to give him 100 <hi>l.</hi> a Year, to Overſee and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern their Manufacture: But ſeeing their Undertaking had not anſwer'd their, or his Expectations, he never received the promiſed Salary, nor diſcounted it to 'em; and if he had, he would certainly have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it (in Mony, Linen, and Coals) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Spinners. Which I the rather adventure to ſay, becauſe when he drew ſome Prizes in one of Mr. <hi>Neal</hi>'s Lotteries, to the Value of 180 <hi>l.</hi> he reſerved to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, only the Mony he had adventured: The Mony gained he gave, partly to ſome Relations, and partly to the Poor.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:97235:18"/>
            <p>But the poor Spinners, being thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> returned to 'em a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and managed that Trade as he was wont: But ſo, that he made it bear al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt its own Charges. But that their ſmaller Wages might be comfortable to them, he was more Charitable to 'em in his diſtributions, than in any former Years; and begged for 'em, of almoſt all Perſons of Rank, with whom he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timacy, or ſo much as Friendſhip. He would alſo carry his Cloth to divers, with whom he ſcarce had any Acquaintance; telling 'em, <hi>it was the Poor's Cloth, which in conſcience they ought to buy at the Price it could be afforded:</hi> If the Buyers were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Wealthy, they muſt alſo give ſome of the Cloth they had bought, in Shirting; and he would quickly ſend for the Mony, that was due for the Cloth. But without theſe Ways, it had been impoſſible for him, to imploy ſuch a multitude of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; who could not ſtay a minute for their Mony. This continued to be his chief buſineſs, and care, to the day of his Death: Saving that about Two Years ſince, when the calling in the Clipped Mony, occaſioned ſuch a Scarcity of Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Coin, that it was hard with many Rich to get Mony enough to go to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97235:18"/>he was forced to diſmiſs ſome of his Spinners, for mere want of Mony to pay 'em. I heard his Partner and Kinſman Mr. <hi>James,</hi> tell him; He had taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 700 <hi>l.</hi> out of their Caſh already, for the Spinners: And that he ſhould take out no more, as yet. Not that Mr. <hi>James</hi> was not always an Encourager and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter of the Work-Houſe Charity; for he never took any Intereſt-mony, for his Share in that Stock: but their whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Trade going thro' the hands of Mr. <hi>James,</hi> and being managed by him; he was more ſenſible than Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> that more ready Mony could not be ſpared to that uſe, without great Diſadvantage to their Trade.</p>
            <p>Flax and Tow being Goods very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtible, Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was always a little uneaſy, leſt by ſome Accident the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, being in the keeping only of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſhould take fire: And I remember, the Boys in one of their licentious times of throwing Squibs, flung one into the Work-houſe Cellar, where the Tow and Flax was ſtowed; but Providence did not permit, it ſhould do any hurt.</p>
            <p>Before I diſmiſs this Work-houſe, I muſt take notice, that at his death our Friend told Dr. <hi>L.</hi> that he did not regret his Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97235:19"/>only he could have been willing (had God ſo pleaſed) to have continued two Months longer, to put his Work-houſe and Spinners into another Method. That Method is now ſettled, by Mr. <hi>James;</hi> and the poor Spinners imploy'd as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>Concerning this Work-houſe, and the Spinners, Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> would often ſay, that, <hi>To pay the Spinners, to relieve 'em with Mony begged for 'em, with Coals, and Shirting, was to him ſuch a Pleaſure; as magnificent Buildings, pleaſant Walks, well cultivated Orchards and Gardens, the Jol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Muſick and Wine, or the Charms of Love or Study, are to others.</hi> I am perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he ſaid no more than the Truth; for Mr. <hi>James,</hi> who was his Apprentice, Journey-man and Partner upwards of thirty Years, gives this Account of his Uncle's Expence on this, and other Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities; [Comparing and balancing his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences and Loſſes with his Gains, he might have left an Eſtate behind him of at leaſt 20000 <hi>l.</hi> if he had not given and ſpent it in publick and private Charities, Buildings, and other good Works; whereas now his Eſtate amounts to no more than a ſixth part of that Sum.] But it was his ſettled Reſolution not to be Richer: He
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97235:19"/>told me, but little before he died, that were he now worth Forty Thouſand Pounds, he would die but very little richer, than he then was. I incline to think, he would have died much Poorer: For ſuch a Sum would have engaged him in ſuch vaſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns for his Province, the Poor; that (probably) he would have gone beyond the Expence he intended at firſt for them. I have heard his Phyſician blame him ſometimes, that he did not allow himſelf competent time for his Dinner; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten'd to <hi>Garraway</hi>'s Coffee-Houſe, about his Affairs. But thoſe Affairs were ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, if ever, his own; he was to ſollicit for the Poor, or in the buſineſs of ſome Friend who wanted Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Intereſt: Or he was to meet on ſome deſign relating to the Publick Good. In theſe matters his Friends, that were not quick in their Diſpatches, had reaſon oftentimes to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of him, as not giving them ſufficient time, to diſpatch Buſineſs with him: For he was nimble above moſt Men, in Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, in Speech, Judgment, Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and Action.</p>
            <p>He was perſuaded by ſome, to make trial of the <hi>Woolen Manufacture;</hi> becauſe at this, the Poor might make better Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, than at Linen-Work. For this, he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97235:20"/>took a Houſe in <hi>Artillery-Lane:</hi> But the Price of Wool advancing very much, and the <hi>London</hi>-Spinſters being almoſt wholly unskilful at Drawing a Woolen-Thread, after a conſiderable Loſs by 'em, and 29 Months trial, he gave off the Project.</p>
            <p>He labour'd with a particular Zeal and Activity, in redeeming poor Debtors out of Priſon; not only as it was Charity to the Perſons, but out of regard to their (in the mean time) diſtreſſed and ſtarved Families: He would ſay, The Releaſe of one Man out of Priſon, is a Relief beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on his whole Family. I have ſure grounds to believe, that it was himſelf of whom he ſpake, in his <hi>Book of Propoſals,</hi> p. 83. <hi>I know one Man, who, in a few Years laſt paſt, with the Charity of ſome Worthy Perſons, has delivered ſome Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of poor People out of Priſon; who lay there, either only for Jailors Fees, or for very ſmall Debts: I have reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that, many more have been delivered by others; and yet one ſhall find the Priſons very full of Priſoners at this time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As he diſcharged great Numbers of <hi>Priſoners,</hi> he took care for the better and eaſier Subſiſtence of others, while in Priſon: For he would examine the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, concerning their Uſage by their
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97235:20"/>Keepers; and ſometimes proſecuted Jai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, before the Judges, for extorting un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Fees, and other exorbitant Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. I remember, one of the Jailors pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> made a Rope, and hanged himſelf before the matter was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined: A ſtrong Preſumption, that he was conſcious to himſelf, of great Faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs; and a demonſtrative Proof, of the great need of ſuch Proſecutions, and of the Virtue of him that undertook 'em.</p>
            <p>He continued theſe Endeavours for poor Debtors, from before the Year 1681. to his laſt Breath: but being grieved, that he could do nothing for Debtors, laid up for great Sums; therefore, on behalf of ſuch he always vigorouſly promoted <hi>Acts of Grace</hi> by Parlament, whereby Inſolvent Debtors were diſcharged. Tho' he never was a Parlament man, he had a mighty Intereſt in both Houſes; and <hi>was the Cauſe</hi> that many Bills were quaſhed, and others paſſed: inſomuch that once, when an Act of Grace for poor Priſoners, that was lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to have, and had an ill uſe made of it by unconſcionable or knaviſh People, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Houſes and Royal Aſſent; he was upbraided with it by ſome of the Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and told, <hi>that it was his Act.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:97235:21"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was not inſenſible, that ſometimes people come into Priſons, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe become poor, more by their own Negligence, Idleneſs, Riot, and Pride, than by Miſhap and Miſadventure; yet he could not join with thoſe, who ſay hereupon, <hi>they hate, the Poor; and that ſuch well deſerve the Straits, and Miſeries, that they bring on themſelves.</hi> He was wont to anſwer, to ſuch Reaſonings, that; <hi>It would be a miſerable World indeed, if the Divine Providence ſhould act by that Rule: if God ſhould ſhow no Favour, grant no Help, or Deliverance, to us, in thoſe Straits or Calamities, that are the effects of our Sins. If the univerſal Lord ſeeks to reclame, and to better us, by Favours, and Graces; do we dare to argue againſt the Example ſet by Him; and againſt a Method, without which, no Man living may ask any thing of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no place whatſoever, but of neceſſity it muſt have divers Poor, more eſpecially <hi>London:</hi> where every Houſe having one or more Servants, who are obliged to ſpend their whole Wages in Clothes; when theſe Servants marry, every little Miſhap in the World reduces 'em to Beggary; their ſmall, or rather no Beginnings are cruſhed, by every Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> had ſo full a Senſe of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97235:21"/>this, that (in ſome Years of his Life) he begged about 500 <hi>l.</hi> a Year; which he diſtributed to the Poor, at their Houſes, or at his own, by the Sums of 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> or 5 <hi>s.</hi> or 10 <hi>s.</hi> or 15 <hi>s.</hi> as he ſaw (or was well inform'd of) the Neceſſities of the Perſons. The way he took, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter effecting this Charitable Diſtribution, was; he would enquire of the moſt noted Perſons for Honeſty and Charity, in the ſeveral Pariſhes, who were the moſt Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitous and beſt Deſerving Poor in that Neighbourhood: He went then to their Houſes, that he might judg farther by their meagre Looks, number of Children, ſorry Furniture, and other Circumſtances, in what proportion it might be fit to aſſiſt 'em. He always took their Names and Numbers into a Book; and ſent a Copy of ſo much of his Book, to the Perſons who had intruſted him with Charity, as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to the Mony truſted to him by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch Perſon: That if he ſo minded, he might make enquiry, by himſelf, or any other, concerning the Truth of the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count given in. But Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Fidelity grew to be ſo well known, that after a few years, divers of his Contributors would not receive his Accounts. I know a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Perſon, whoſe hand was with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97235:22"/>Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> in all his Charities; I ſhould not exceed (I believe) if I ſaid, that in <hi>Twenty One Years</hi> time he hath given by Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s hand, or at his Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, <hi>Five</hi> or <hi>Six Thouſand Pounds:</hi> this Perſon hath himſelf told me, that Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was wont to bring him the Accounts of his Disburſments, till he was even weary of 'em, and (becauſe he was ſo well aſſured of him) he deſired him, not to bring him any more. Sometimes the Sums brought, or ſent in, to Mr. <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> for the Poor, were ſuch, as did ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble him to ſpare ſome part to ſome whom he knew to be charitably diſpos'd like himſelf: In that caſe, he would ſend ſmall Sums, ſuch as 40 <hi>s.</hi> or 3 <hi>l.</hi> ſometimes more, to thoſe his Acquaintance, which Sums they were to divide, among the Poor of their Vicinage; whoſe Names and Caſe thoſe Friends were to return to him. He hath ſent to me, and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that I know of, many ſuch Sums; in <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Time, in Hard Weather, and Times of Scarcity.</p>
            <p>In theſe Diſtributions, Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time conſidered others, beſides the mere Poor; particularly the poorer ſort of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters: I doubt not he hath made uſe of many hands beſides mine; but by me he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97235:22"/>hath ſent (of his own proper motion) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times the Sum of 40 <hi>s.</hi> ſometimes two Guineas, to Miniſters that were good Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and Exemplary, but their Vicarige, Curacy, or Lecture ſmall. I have known that he has ſent no leſs than 10 <hi>l.</hi> to a Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyman in Debt, or oppreſt with many Children; when he hath been well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the Perſon was a Man of Probity and Merit. He asked me once, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>P.</hi> of <hi>Gr. Ch.</hi> what ſort of Man he was? I anſwer'd; his Mind was much above his Purſe; He was Charitable, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, Learned; a Father among young Scholars, who were promiſing Men; but his Living not above 80 <hi>l.</hi> or 90 <hi>l.</hi> a Year. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> ſaid; <hi>I have done conſiderable for that man:</hi> I anſwer'd, as I thought my ſelf obliged; You may take it on my Word, that your Liberality was never better placed. Afterwards I met the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Mr. <hi>P.</hi> in <hi>London;</hi> I deſired her to accept half a Pint of Wine, at the next Tavern: While we were together, I asked her, Whether there had not been ſome Acquaintance between her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and Mr. <hi>Firmin.</hi> She ſaid, The Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance was not much; but the Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip great. She ſaid, Her Husband was acquainted with many Perſons of Quality,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97235:23"/>that he had experienced their Liberality thro' the whole courſe of his Life: becauſe his Addreſs, as well as his Merit, was ſo remarkable. She ſaid; that of ſo many Benefactors to Mr. <hi>P.</hi> Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> had done moſt for him, both in Life and Death. When her Husband died, his Eſtate would not pay his Debts; ſhe was adviſed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, by a Clergyman, to propoſe a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition with the Creditors: that ſeeing every one could not be fully pay'd, yet all of 'em might receive part of their Debt. She conſulted Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> by Letter, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this; he approved the Advice, and was one of the firſt that ſubſcribed the Compoſition: but withal, ſent her a Letter, wherein he remitted his whole Debt; and deſired to ſee her, when her Affair was cleared, and ſhe at quiet. When ſhe came to him, he ſaid, <hi>He had miſſed in his aim, in what he deſign'd to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure for her, but he would do ſomething him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:</hi> Shortly after, he ſent her a good <hi>Norwich</hi> Stuff, that very well clothed her, and her Four Children. She told me this, with many Tears; to which I had the more regard, becauſe I had long known her to be a Virtuous, and very Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Woman.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:97235:23"/>
            <p>As Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Pains, and Care in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving forth theſe Charities, were not ſmall; ſo neither were they little, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing them: Not only becauſe many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are hardly perſwaded, to give the Bread of themſelves and Families to others; but becauſe 'tis much more difficult to beg for others, than to give ones ſelf. He that begs for others, muſt be Maſter of a great deal of Prudence, as well as Wit, and Addreſs: He muſt know, how to chooſe the <hi>Mollia tempora fandi,</hi> the fitteſt opportunity of ſpeaking; and when he ſpeaks, he muſt apply himſelf to thoſe paſſions of the Perſon, by which only he can be wrought on. I remember Mr. <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> told me, of his applying to a Citizen of the higheſt rank, for his Charity in rebuilding St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Hoſpital: Of whom he demanded no leſs than 100 <hi>l.</hi> The Perſon had been ſome way diſobliged by the Governours of that Hoſpital; ſo he refuſed to ſubſcribe any thing: But our Friend ſeeing him one day among ſome Friends whom he reſpected, and by whom he was willing to be reſpected; and that alſo he was in a very good Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; he puſh'd on his Requeſt for the Hoſpital, and prevailed with him ſo far, as to ſubſcribe the whole 100 <hi>l.</hi> But to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97235:24"/>his perſonal Solicitations, he was forced ſometimes to add Letters; and ſometimes ſucceeded by the Arguments in his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, better than by the Authority of his perſonal Mediation. I find in one of his Books, in the Year 1679. the Sum of 520 <hi>l.</hi> 6 <hi>s.</hi> received of ſeventy two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; in a Book of the Year 1681. the Sum of 531 <hi>l.</hi> 19 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> received of forty three Perſons. All theſe were to be treated with, privately, and opportunely; which required much Time, Caution, Induſtry, and Diſcretion: which laid out on his own Buſineſs, what great Effects would it have produced? Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> might, much more eaſily, have been one of the great Men of the World, than Almoner General for the Poor, and the Hoſpitals. I obſerve in the ſame Book of 1681. that the Disburſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt the Sum 531 <hi>l.</hi> 19 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> do amount to 594:15:11. the Balance over paid is 62:15:5. which over-paid Balance is to be found in many of his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, and I believe it came out of his own Purſe. I muſt note alſo, that the Sums were not given for the Poor alone, or for the Spinners alone; but of 50 <hi>l.</hi> given, 30 of it is for the Spinners, and 20 for the Poor, ſometimes 20 for the Spinners and 30 for the Poor: Elſewhere 100 <hi>l.</hi> is given,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97235:24"/>50 for the Poor, and 50 for Spinners; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother gives 50 <hi>l.</hi> for Cloth, to be divided to the Poor; Another 100 <hi>l.</hi> for the ſame uſe.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> having ſet his heart ſo much on Charity, could not but eſteem and love Mr. <hi>Gouge;</hi> a Man of the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: whom, while he was in <hi>London,</hi> he got to table with him. 'Tis not to be doubted, that 'twas the intimate Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of theſe two Perſons, that gave occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to that (remarkable) paſſage, in Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi>'s Funeral Sermon on Mr. <hi>Gouge,</hi> p. 82. <q>Mr. <hi>Gouge</hi> was of a diſpoſition, ready to imbrace and oblige all Men; allowing others to differ from him, even in Opinions that were very Dear to him. Provided, Men did but <hi>fear God, and work Righteouſneſs;</hi> he loved them heartily, how diſtant ſoever from him in Judgment about leſs Neceſſary things: in which he is worthy to be propounded as an Example, to Men of all Perſuaſions.</q> And till the Example is followed, the World will never have Peace.</p>
            <p>That great Preacher has given us an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, of Mr. <hi>Gouges</hi> Religious Charity in printing divers good Books, in the <hi>Welch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongues; to be given
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97235:25"/>to thoſe that were Poor, and ſold to ſuch as could buy them: the Chief of thoſe Prints, and the moſt Expenſive, was an Edition of the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Liturgie</hi> in the <hi>Welch</hi> Tongue; no fewer than Eight Thouſand Copies, of this Work, were printed together. One cannot queſtion, that Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> contributed to, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured divers Sums for this excellent Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking of his Friend; tho' all is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to Mr. <hi>Gouge,</hi> who was Chief in that great and good Work. After Mr. <hi>Gouge</hi>'s Death, I find the Sum of 419 <hi>l.</hi> 9 <hi>s.</hi> given to buy a Number of thoſe <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles;</hi> whereof Dr. <hi>Tillotſon</hi> (then Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s) gave 50 <hi>l.</hi> Mr. <hi>Morrice</hi> 67 <hi>l.</hi> other Perſons the reſt: but there wants in the Receipts 26 <hi>l.</hi> 13 <hi>s.</hi> to balance the Disburſment; and that, I judg, was Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s mony.</p>
            <p>Now that we are ſpeaking of <hi>Books,</hi> I ought not to forget, that Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten printed Ten thouſand Copies of the <hi>Scripture-Catechiſm;</hi> which ſome think was written by Dr. <hi>Worthington:</hi> But I have cauſe to believe, that the Author was Dr. <hi>Fowler,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Gloceſter;</hi> who in compiling it, followed the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Dr. <hi>Worthington.</hi> Theſe Mr. <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> gave to his Spinners, and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97235:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>and to the Children of the Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal: engaging them to get it by heart; and giving ſomething to thoſe that did. He lodged alſo great Numbers of them with Bookſellers, at cheaper rates than they were printed, that they might be ſold alſo cheaper; and thereby, be diſperſed all over <hi>England.</hi> His Acquaintance might, at all times, have of them what Numbers they would, <hi>gratis.</hi> He valued this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, becauſe 'tis wholly in the Words of Scripture; favours no particular Party or Perſuaſion, and therefore is of general Uſe: the Aim of the Judicious Author be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to inſtruct the Youth, and the Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, in what <hi>all Parties agree</hi> is neceſſary to be believ'd, and done; leaving it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to engage 'em in Controverſies and Debates.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1680. and 1681. came over the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants; new work for Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Charity and Zeal: for of all the Objects of Charity, he thought thoſe the moſt Deſerving, who were undone for Conſcience toward God; whether ſuch Conſcience be a well-inform'd Conſcience, or an erroneous and miſtaken. 'Tis not the truth or falſhood of the Opinion, but the Zeal for God, and the ſincerity to the dictates of Conſcience, that makes the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97235:26"/>Martyr. Therefore now our Elemoſinary General had to beg, not only for the Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the Poor of the out-Pariſhes of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> the Redemption of Debtors from Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for Coals, and Shirting; but for a vaſt number of Religious Refugees, whoſe Wants required not only a great, but an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Succour. The firſt, and one of the moſt difficult Cares for them, was, how to provide Lodgings for ſuch multitudes, in a City where Lodgings are as coſtly as Diet? But Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> bethought him of the <hi>Peſt-Houſe,</hi> then empty of Patients: the Motion was approv'd by the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> and <hi>Court of Aldermen;</hi> and ſome Hundreds of theſe Strangers were accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated in that ſpatious and convenient Place. As for Relief in Mony, they made their firſt application to the <hi>French Church:</hi> therefore I find in Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Books, <hi>Delivered to the Deacons of the</hi> French <hi>Church</hi> 50 l. <hi>to</hi> J. S. 10 l. <hi>to an old Man at</hi> Ipſwich 20 l. This was immediately up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their coming over. In 1681 and 1682, I find the Sum of 2363 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> 1 <hi>d.</hi> iſſued forth for the uſe of the <hi>French</hi> thro' his hands; and in 1683, for the <hi>French</hi> Children at <hi>Ware</hi> 443 <hi>l.</hi> 18 <hi>s.</hi> 9 <hi>d.</hi> For their Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Houſe at <hi>Rye</hi> 20 <hi>l.</hi> I find upon his Books theſe following Sums, before a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97235:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Brief</hi> was granted to them, 100 <hi>l.</hi> then 155 <hi>l.</hi> in the next page 70 <hi>l.</hi> 15 <hi>s.</hi> To anſwer theſe Receipts, the Books ſay, Sept. 15. <hi>Delivered to Mr.</hi> Carbonel, <hi>&amp;c. in</hi> 16 <hi>pieces of Cloth,</hi> 50 l. Sept. 24. <hi>To the Deacons at the</hi> Savoy, <hi>in Cloth,</hi> 20 l. Oct. 7. <hi>To</hi> Carbon, <hi>&amp;c. in</hi> 32 <hi>pieces of Cloth,</hi> 100 l. 14 <hi>s.</hi> The balance is 27 <hi>l.</hi> 8 <hi>s.</hi> which ('tis likely) was his own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1682. he ſet up a Linen Manufacture for the French at <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> to which himſelf gave 100 <hi>l.</hi> which was all ſunk in their Service, ſaving that at laſt he received 8 <hi>l.</hi> 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi> He paid alſo for their Meeting-Houſe at <hi>Ipſwich</hi> 13 <hi>l.</hi> In the ſame Year alſo he disburſed for them for Coals 60 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> whereof he received only 20 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> There have been Four Briefs granted to the French, one by K. <hi>Charles</hi> in 1681. a ſecond by K. <hi>James</hi> in 1686. another by K. <hi>James</hi> in 1687. the fourth by K. <hi>William</hi> in 1693. Beſides which, K. <hi>William</hi> gave to 'em 1000 <hi>l. per</hi> Month for 39 Months. It was Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> that was chiefly concerned in the diſtribution of all this Mony; eſpecially of the Thirty Nine Thouſand Pounds, which was committed to two Biſhops, two Knights, and a Gentleman; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97235:27"/>the whole Diſtribution was left to Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> ſometimes <hi>with,</hi> but more commonly <hi>without</hi> their Inſpection. I ſee I have omitted, before I was aware, the following Sums, paid to the French Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants at <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> before their Brief was collected; 45 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> and 42 <hi>l.</hi> and 45 <hi>l.</hi> 9 <hi>s.</hi> another 42 <hi>l.</hi> to 21 Families at <hi>Ipſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had a principal hand in the ſpecial Collections, that are now made every Winter, about <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> time, in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, for the Poor in and about <hi>London.</hi> He was the man that ſolicited the King's Letter for making thoſe Collections; he took care of printing and diſtributing the King's and Biſhop of <hi>London</hi>'s Letters to the ſeveral Rectors, and other Miniſters, of Churches in <hi>London,</hi> to be by them read in their reſpective Churches. He waited on the Lords of the Treaſury for the King's part of that Charity: And when the Mony, as well of the King as the Pariſhes, was collected, and paid into the Chamber of <hi>London,</hi> and was then to be divided, among the Poor of the ſeveral Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, by my Lords the Biſhop and May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or of <hi>London;</hi> no man could ſo well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion their Dividends as Mr. <hi>Firmin.</hi> This was well known to their Lordſhips,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97235:27"/>who, therefore, ſeldom made any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his Diſtributions. In theſe matters, all the Church-Wardens made their appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to Mr. <hi>Firmin;</hi> and when the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidend was ſettled, received their War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants from him: For which purpoſe, the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> would many times en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt him with Blanks, and my Lord Mayor was always ready to give his Hand. The whole of this Charity was ſo conſtantly, and ſo many years, managed by Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> that, he dying ſome days before <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> laſt, the King's Letter, for the Collection, was not given till the 12th of <hi>January:</hi> And when the Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was brought in from the ſeveral Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, they were at a loſs for the Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and were glad to take direction from Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Pattern.</p>
            <p>There hath been occaſion in my laſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to mention the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> (Dr. <hi>Henry Compton</hi>) I ought not to omit, that Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> could never ſpeak of this Biſhop, without a particular reſpect and deference: He admired the Candor, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, Wiſdom, and Dexterity, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied and tempered by Caution and Vigor; which (ſaid he often) are ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in his Lordſhip, and ſo conſtantly appear upon all occaſions, proper to any
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97235:28"/>of thoſe Virtues, that I wiſh it were as eaſy to be like, as 'tis impoſſible not to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem him. I return to Mr. <hi>Firmin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During the laſt 23 or 24 years of his Life, he was one of the Governours of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> Hoſpital in <hi>London.</hi> 'Tis known to every body almoſt in <hi>London,</hi> that Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> procured a great number, and very conſiderable Donations to this Hoſpital; but I cannot ſpecifie many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, becauſe he kept not exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts of 'em; but thoſe that have come to my knowledg, are remarkable; of one of which give me leave to give the Reader this account. The Honourable Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> having had it in his thoughts to make a proviſion for a Mathematical Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in that Hoſpital, became the hapy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer, and (by his intereſt in the then Lord Treaſurer <hi>Clifford,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Howard</hi>) the ſucceſsful Procurer of the eſtabliſhment of a Mathematical School in that Hoſpital, for the conſtant breeding of the number of 40 Boys, skill'd in the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue, to a perfect knowledg in the Art of Navigation. The occaſion thus. There was 7000 <hi>l.</hi> given to this Hoſpital, by a Citizen, (payable out of <hi>Weavers-Hall</hi>) for the maintenance of 40 Boys: Upon the Reſtoration, the Fund,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97235:28"/>out of which this iſſued, reverting to the Crown, King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d.</hi> upon the ſaid Propoſal and Petition to that purpoſe, was graciouſly pleaſed to grant to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital the ſaid 7000 <hi>l.</hi> to be paid them by 1000 <hi>l. per Annum</hi> for 7 years; upon which the Hoſpital was obliged to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the ſaid 40 Boys, ſucceſſively to be ſo educated for ever. Sir <hi>Robert Clayton</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greatly pleas'd that he had been an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in ſo charitable and beneficial a Conſtitution, did afterwards meditate a Donation from himſelf to this Hoſpital, and ſo to take it into his ſpecial Care and Beneficence. And that which inſtigated him to theſe thoughts, was, he had la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured under a very grievous ſickneſs, even to deſpair of recovery; but it pleaſed the Almighty Governour that he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, and Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was very inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in it, both by his perſonal miniſtry, and giving quick notices to Phyſicians of ſeveral ſymptoms. Hereupon, Sir <hi>Robert</hi> adviſeth with Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> about the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and adding a Ward for Girls to this Hoſpital, as a teſtimony of his gratitude to God; and determined that Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> ſhould have the management of that Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair. Accordingly he went about it, you may be ſure with great Alacrity and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97235:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>but at whoſe charge he erected this large Building was a ſecret, not known to any of the Family but <hi>John Morris</hi> Eſq Sir <hi>Robert</hi>'s Partner in this Work alſo; and perhaps to my Lady: In this was laid out near 4000 <hi>l.</hi> but it was not yet finiſht, when upon occaſion of the unhappy Difference between the Paſſive-Obedience Men and the Law-Obedience Men, the former having the power on their ſide, turn'd out the latter both out of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the City and of that Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, among whom Sir <hi>Robert</hi> (tho' emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent) was ejected, together with his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Agent and Friend Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Governour as I have ſaid. Then it was that Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> broke ſilence, and upbraided thoſe excluding Governours with depriving the Hoſpital of ſuch a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor as the Builder of that Ward. For Sir <hi>Robert</hi> was now alone, Mr. <hi>Morris</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deceaſed, and having left him the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of his Eſtate. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> alſo built a Ward for the Sick, to prevent infecting the Healthy and Sound; if the ſmall Pox, or other contagious diſtemper, ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen among the Children, as it often doth. This Ward coſt 426 <hi>l.</hi> 4 <hi>s.</hi> beſides 6 <hi>l.</hi> 5 <hi>s.</hi> for a Preſs; but the Gentleman that gave the mony for both, would not then be
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97235:29"/>known; and continues ſtill of the ſame mind. I find, however, an account in Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Books of 1537 <hi>l.</hi> (the Sick Ward included) received, and laid out by Mr. <hi>Firmin:</hi> And another account of 704 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>d.</hi> received, with the names of the Perſons who gave it, and the uſes for which it was given. In the Year of our Lord 1675, our Friend built two Houſes for the two Beadles, or other Officers of the Hoſpital, at his own charge; of which I have a Certificate, under the Clerk's hand, in theſe words. <q>At his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per coſt and charges, Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> ſet up a Clock and Dial, for the uſe of the Hoſpital, at the top of the North-end of the great Hall. The ſaid Mr. <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> built two new brick Houſes in the <hi>Town-ditch,</hi> one at the South-Weſt end, the other at the North-Eaſt, to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed to ſuch Officers, as the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Hoſpital ſhould think fit. Farther, at his own coſt and charge, a Shed, or little Room, at the Eaſt-end of the late Bowling-Ally; and a new brick Wall: he repaired all the Walls, and levelled the Ground.</q>
            </p>
            <p>At the charge of a Friend of his, a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen, he laid Leaden Pipes to convey the Water to the ſeveral Offices of the Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97235:30"/>and bought them a large Ciſtern; which in all coſt about 200 <hi>l.</hi> theſe were great Conveniences to the Houſe, and the Orphans, who before fetched up the water they uſed on their backs; which agreed not well with their ſtrength, kept the Houſe foul, and prejudiced their Clothes. Out of Town he built a School, with all conveniences to it, for the Hoſpital Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; this he ſet up at <hi>Hartford,</hi> where many of the Hoſpital Children are Boar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: the School coſt 544 <hi>l.</hi> 13 <hi>s.</hi> of which he received, by the Charity of ten per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the ſum of 488 <hi>l.</hi> the balance is 56 <hi>l.</hi> 13 <hi>s.</hi> which lies upon himſelf for any thing that appears. He was wont every Lord's-day, at five in the evening, to ſee the Orphans of the Hoſpital at their Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſervice; at what time they prayed, and ſung an <hi>Anthem</hi> by ſelect Voices, the Chorus by all the Boys. After this, they ſate down to Supper at the ſeveral Tables, under the care of their Matrons: here Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> viewed them in their Proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in the Behaviour both of them and their Officers and Attendents, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending, or admoniſhing, as there was occaſion. To this Sight he invited, one time or other, all his Friends, whether of the Town or Country; and at laſt led
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97235:30"/>'em to the Orphans Box, into which they would put ſomewhat, more or leſs, as they were charitably diſpoſed. A Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-man was very remarkable: for having ſeen the Order, and Methods of the Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal; when he came home, he made his Will, and gave very conſiderably to the place. I was once with our Friend at the Hoſpital, when looking over the Childrens Supper, which was Pudding-pies, he took notice of a Pye that ſeemed not of due big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; he took it immediately into the Kitchin, and weighed it himſelf; but it proved down-weight.</p>
            <p>Theſe Cares did not ſo wholly imploy this active man, but that he was alſo a great and good Common-wealths-man. He was always mindful of thoſe who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for Conſcience, or for Aſſerting the Rights and Liberties of the Nation: And he printed a great many Sheets, and ſome Books, of that tendency and nature; great numbers of which he himſelf diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. When King <hi>James</hi> commanded the reading his Declaration (for Toleration and Indulgence in Religion) in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; a great number of well-wrote Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets were printed and diſperſed, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince people of the bad deſign of that ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Declaration; Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97235:31"/>principal encourager and promoter of thoſe Prints, which coſt him conſiderable ſums, as well for their publication as otherways. He furthered, as much as in him lay, the Heroical Attempt of the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> to reſcue this Nation from Slavery and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery: And ſince His Majeſty has been ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the Throne, our Friend has been particularly diligent in promoting the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture of the <hi>Luſtring Company;</hi> becauſe it is highly Beneficial to this Nation, and as Prejudicial to our (then) Enemy. He had the greateſt hand, and uſed the moſt effectual endeavours, for procuring Acts of Parliament, and Rules of Court, in that behalf.</p>
            <p>He and Mr. <hi>Renew</hi> took great pains, and were at much expence, to prevent Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with <hi>France,</hi> and the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Silks, and other Commodities from thence: For this, they ran the hazard of their lives, from the revenge of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and others, whom they proſecuted to Execution. A Merchant was ſo deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately angry at his Detection, and the great Damage he ſhould unavoidably ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain thereby, that he went into a room alone, in a Tavern, and ended his Life by ſhooting himſelf into the head. The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents of Mr. <hi>Renew</hi> and Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> gave
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97235:31"/>either the firſt, or very early intelligence of the <hi>French</hi> Invaſion; which was to have followed the Aſſaſſination of the King.</p>
            <p>But he was not more a Friend to the Liberties of the Nation, and to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Eſtabliſhment, than he was an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Licentiouſneſs. He was from the firſt a Member of <hi>the Society for the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Manners;</hi> he contributed to it by his Advice, Aſſiſtance, Solicitations, as much as his leiſure from the cares and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours (before mentioned and exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) would permit him: but his Purſe was always with them. He had ſuch a zeal againſt needleſs Swearing, whereby the Religion of an Oath grows vile and contemptible, and Falſe-ſwearing becomes almoſt as common as idle and unneceſſary Swearing, to the indelible ſcandal of the Chriſtian name, and the great danger (even as far as Life and Eſtate) of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons: I ſay his Zeal againſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon needleſs Swearing, in what form ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, was ſo great, that in Coffee-Houſes, or other places, where he over-heard ſuch Swearing, he would immediately challenge the Forfeiture (appointed by Law) for the uſe of the Poor; ſo that in Companies, where he was frequent, an Oath was ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97235:32"/>heard. But he raiſed the forfeiture according to the quality of the perſon; if a Noble-Man, or other perſon of diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or a Clergyman ſwore, they came not off at the ordinary forfeiture, appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Law, it was doubled or trebled upon them; eſpecially, if any ſuch were very common Swearers, or their Oaths of a profane or impious ſort. If any perſon refuſed to pay the forfeiture required; our Friend would tell 'em, the forfeiture was to the Poor, whoſe Collector and Steward he was: if ſtill they refuſed to pay, their puniſhment (he told them) was, to be ſet down, by him, in the liſt of his <hi>Incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible Swearers;</hi> and that, for the future, he would not own them as his Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or ſpeak to 'em as ſuch. Divers Noble Perſons would not endure this laſt; but would immediately condeſcend to pay the forfeiture, or promiſe payment, the which he ſeldom remitted; chiefly if they were often in that fault. As for himſelf, I never heard an Oath from him in 44 years (almoſt daily) Converſation with him; tho' his temper was naturally quick and warm; and he had often great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations to Anger, one of the principal cauſes of raſh and intemperate Swearing.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:97235:32"/>
            <p>But let us return to Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities. No body can have forgot the great number of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Nobility, Clergy, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and others of all qualities, and both Sexes, who fled into <hi>England</hi> from the Perſecution, and Proſcriptions of K. <hi>James.</hi> A Brief was granted to 'em, of which Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was one of the Commiſſioners; but beſides that, the Miniſters, Church-Wardens, and Collectors of every Pariſh in <hi>England,</hi> were to give account by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Mr. <hi>Firmin,</hi> what Sums they had col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, and paid to the Arch-Deacons. Therefore, on many Poſt-days, ſeveral hundred Letters came to his hand, for a long time: and many of the collected Sums were ſent to him, and by him paid into the Chamber of <hi>London;</hi> the Mony given by the King and Queen was wholly, in a manner, Solicited and Received by him. The Numbers and Neceſſities of theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugees required a ſecond Brief; the Sum Total (paid to theſe two Briefs) that went through Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s hands, was Fifty ſix thouſand five hundred ſixty ſix Pounds, Seven Shillings and Six Pence. The diſtribution of the Mony, gathered on theſe Briefs, was by ſuch a number of the Commiſſioners; but Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was the moſt conſtant Man at their meetings:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97235:33"/>ſometimes he attended the Diſtribution from Morning to Night, without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for food. But beſides the Sums paid into the Chamber, and diſtributed as aforeſaid, I am aſſur'd our Friend ſolicited, and gave many private Sums to particular Perſons, whoſe Quality made 'em aſham'd to take of the common Stock, or whoſe Neceſſities required more than (without giving offence) could be allowed out of it. When by the Mercy of GOD, and the Magnanimity of the King, <hi>Ireland</hi> was reduced, and the Proteſtants might now return to their Houſes, Employs, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates; Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> doubled his Induſtry and Diligence to furniſh them for their Journey; becauſe thereby he not only ſerved them, but eaſed the Nation, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the better (that is, the Charitable) part of it. He obtained great Sums for this purpoſe; Sir <hi>Tho. Cook</hi> (to whom I think it a debt to name him) gave 1500 <hi>l.</hi> to this Service, apprehending it a Charity to <hi>England,</hi> as well as to the poor Sufferers. See here a Letter from the moſt Reverend the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Tuam,</hi> and Seven o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; all of them, I think, Biſhops of that Kingdom; I am ſure moſt of them are.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:97235:33"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>To Mr. <hi>THO. FIRMIN.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>BEing occaſionally met together at <hi>Dublin,</hi> on a Public Account; and often diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing of the great Relief, which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of this Kingdom found among their Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> in the time of our late Miſeries: We cannot treat that Subject without as frequent mention of your Name, who ſo chearfully and entirely devoted your ſelf to that Miniſtry. We conſider, with all thankfulneſs, how much the public Charity was improved by your Induſtry; and we are Witneſſes of your Indefatigable Pains and Faithfulneſs in the Diſtribution; by which, many Thouſands were preſerved from Periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. We know alſo, that ſome who refuſed to take out of the Common Stock, as being deſirous to cut off occaſion of Murmurs, were however, by your Mediation, comfortably ſubſiſted by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Benevolences. We doubt not, but you and they have the earneſt of your Reward in the peace of your minds; which, we pray God to ſill with Comforts, and <hi>Illuminate with His Truths;</hi> making His Grace to abound in them, who have abounded in their Charity to others. And we intreat, that you, and all ſuch as you know to have had their parts in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97235:34"/>this Service, would believe, that we ſhall ever retain a grateful remembrance of it; as ſome Teſtimony whereof, we deſire you, for your ſelf in particular, to receive this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of your Kindneſs to our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and therein to</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your much Obliged, and moſt Humble Servants,</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Jo. Tuam,</item>
                           <item>W. Clonfert,</item>
                           <item>Bar. Fernleigh,</item>
                           <item>S. Elpin,</item>
                           <item>Edw. Cork and Roſs,</item>
                           <item>N. Waterford,</item>
                           <item>R. Clogher,</item>
                           <item>W. Raploe.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Certainly, a Letter very worthy of their Epiſcopal Character; and which I have inſerted into theſe Memoirs, as much out of Regard and Reverence to them, as for the ſake of Mr. <hi>Firmin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not, I believe, diſpleaſe the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if I add a Poem, addreſſed to Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> by a Clergyman of that Kingdom, and (unleſs I much miſtake) a Dean there.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:97235:34"/>
            <lg>
               <head>On the incomparable Charity, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Induſtry, of Mr. <hi>Tho. Firmin,</hi> in Relieving the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Refugees.</head>
               <l>WHen the late <hi>James</hi> from King to Tyrant fell,</l>
               <l>And for damn'd Stratagems did ranſack hell,</l>
               <l>His lawleſs Claim, by his unlawful Tricks,</l>
               <l>He forfeits, and himſelf from th' Throne he kicks.</l>
               <l>His perjur'd Power he put in <hi>Iriſh</hi> hands,</l>
               <l>Cutting Truth's throat, and ours, t' retrieve their Lands;</l>
               <l>Shepherd and Sheep were chas'd by Beaſts of prey,</l>
               <l>Or Men more greedy after Blood than they:</l>
               <l>For theſe firſt ſlaughter Souls, and then they ſay,</l>
               <l>For th' good of them, they muſt the Bodies ſlay;</l>
               <l>Leſt turning into Hereticks agen,</l>
               <l>They tranſubſtantiate into worſer Men.</l>
               <l>To ſhun theſe Meritorious Acts we fled,</l>
               <l>Quitting our Land, on Water to beg Bread;</l>
               <l>To ſhun the Storm, we did embrace the Waves</l>
               <l>And Winds, leſs cruel than the breath of Slaves;</l>
               <l>Finding that faithleſs Element more kind,</l>
               <l>For we were ſav'd, ſome drown'd we left behind.</l>
               <l>Sea-monſters are not half ſuch thirſty Foes</l>
               <l>For <hi>Engliſh</hi> Blood, as are the <hi>Mac's</hi> and <hi>Oo's.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And when on Board we ſtill fear'd <hi>Teaguiſh</hi> Traps,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they're call'd the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Seas in Maps:</l>
               <l>Except good Conſcience we came ſtripp'd of all,</l>
               <l>Which we our <hi>Naked Truth</hi> may truly call.</l>
               <l>With glad yet heavy hearts we ſaw this Shore;</l>
               <l>So many Tears ne'er ſwell'd the Tides before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Weeping Scene ſoon mov'd the <hi>Royal Pair,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To recommend us to the Kingdom's Care.</l>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:97235:35"/>
               <l>A ſelect number, both of Good and Great,</l>
               <l>Did give, and portion out, our Monthly Treat.</l>
               <l>But our vaſt Numbers, and the various Sums,</l>
               <l>The clamorous Poor (which hither daily comes)</l>
               <l>Weary'd the Managers, who ſoon let all</l>
               <l>On Indefatigable <hi>Firmin</hi> fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>FIRMIN,</hi> our Prop, and our Foundation too,</l>
               <l>Who Raiſed and Built up our Hopes anew;</l>
               <l>Like gen'rous Wine, he ſeem'd by Age to grow</l>
               <l>Stronger, not Sowrer; and he ne'er ran low.</l>
               <l>But let the Braſen Leaves of his freſh Fame,</l>
               <l>Ring thro' the World the Praiſes of his Name:</l>
               <l>And let the Eccho's of his Virtues run,</l>
               <l>To Regions far beyond the Setting <hi>Sun.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>May his loud Morals gloriouſly reſound,</l>
               <l>Where either Men or Angels may be found.</l>
               <l>May he the Things above ne'er beg in vain,</l>
               <l>Who fed of Beggers ſuch a num'rous Train.</l>
               <l>He 'ſpous'd our Wants to ſuch a high degree,</l>
               <l>As if we'd all been his own Family;</l>
               <l>His hand, ſtretch'd forth, gave courſe unto our blood,</l>
               <l>There is no Circulation without Food:</l>
               <l>But all his Dividends did <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nions prove,</l>
               <l>Tying us faſter in the Bonds of Love.</l>
               <l>His Tongue ſo feelingly our Wants declar'd,</l>
               <l>As if with us in Miſery he ſhar'd;</l>
               <l>If Preachers mov'd their Congregations, he</l>
               <l>Mov'd Preachers more, that they would fervent be.</l>
               <l>Pity ſo faſt into his heart diſtill'd,</l>
               <l>'Twas like to burſt the Veſſel which it fill'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As Miniſtring Spirits fly about, ſo he</l>
               <l>In Works like theirs, ſeems all Activity:</l>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:97235:35"/>
               <l>But if the Chariot thus Aethereal prove;</l>
               <l>How Rarify'd the Soul which does it move!</l>
               <l>And thus breaks forth from its too narrow ſtation,</l>
               <l>To animate the body of a <hi>whole Nation;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And is ſo full of Charitable Fire,</l>
               <l>That like <hi>Elias</hi> ſure it muſt retire.</l>
               <l>Till then, he acts the Guardian-Angel's Charge,</l>
               <l>Afflicted Men to Succour and Enlarge;</l>
               <l>And daily does that Heavenly Leſſon learn,</l>
               <l>To Act for others without Self-concern;</l>
               <l>S' entirely making our Int'reſt his <hi>own,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As if he had been born for us alone.</l>
               <l>Tho' great and many were his own Affairs,</l>
               <l>He lays them by; for us were all his Cares;</l>
               <l>And that he might the more with us agree,</l>
               <l>He ſeem'd t' have loſt all things as well as we.</l>
               <l>If we were Baniſh'd from all Worldly Wealth,</l>
               <l>He his Eſtate did Baniſh from himſelf.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who'll then call that <hi>Faith</hi> bad, that does ſo well?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Without Works to Believe,</hi> belongs to Hell.</l>
               <l>And if by Faith Works live, we may him ſtile,</l>
               <l>The Father of the Faithful of our Iſle.</l>
               <l>Scripture is <hi>Creed;</hi> for Chriſtians went to Bliſs</l>
               <l>By th' light of that, before compiling <hi>this.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Go on in <hi>Acting,</hi> for Faith moves by Love;</l>
               <l>They're Twins, that labour here, and live above.</l>
               <l>Wiſdom and Pow'r were Terrible in <hi>God,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Were't not for th' Attribute of being Good:</l>
               <l>So Chriſtians not for Thoughts or Speculation</l>
               <l>Are ſav'd, but by <hi>Acts</hi> of Regeneration;</l>
               <l>Goodneſs attempers all, in Man and Maker,</l>
               <l>And may (for ought I know) ev'n ſave a <hi>Quaker.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:97235:36"/>
               <l>Faith the true Life o'th' Juſt is ſaid to be;</l>
               <l>But th' Life of Faith conſiſts in Charity.</l>
               <l>Thus his Faith is no ſingle Star or Notion,</l>
               <l>But th' chain of Graces in a Conſtellation,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Iriſh</hi> Bodies moſt reſpects; for we</l>
               <l>Were all eclips'd till'ts Influence ſet us free.</l>
               <l>His <hi>Moral</hi> Faith for us ſo current went,</l>
               <l>It paſt for Thouſands when the Briefs were ſpent:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ours</hi> could not go ſo far. He to raiſe more,</l>
               <l>Did make his Charity to run on Score;</l>
               <l>Contracting for <hi>Chance</hi> Mony <hi>certain</hi> Debt:</l>
               <l>So we enjoy'd what he perhaps wants yet.</l>
               <l>His Love ſo great, that like us he would be,</l>
               <l>Truſting to Providence as well as we.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am no Poet; but theſe Lines have writ</l>
               <l>To ſhew the World my Gratitude, not Wit.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthankfulneſs would Diſingenuous be,</l>
               <l>Beyond the want of Ingenuity.</l>
               <l>Therefore let all who are oblig'd, and can,</l>
               <l>Bring ſome ſmall Offering to this God-like Man:</l>
               <l>That our Reſentments may to after-Ages,</l>
               <l>Embalm his Merits in a few kind Pages.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>In <hi>April</hi> 1693. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> enter'd upon part of the care of another <hi>Hoſpital,</hi> that of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> in <hi>Southwark:</hi> a Foundation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the Relief of all ſorts of Lame, or wounded, or Sick Perſons, till they are recovered by the application of proper Medicines, and other means, and by the ſervice of the Phyſicians and Chyrurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97235:36"/>of the Hoſpital. Sir <hi>Rob. Clayton,</hi> (now Father of the City of <hi>London</hi>) being, upon the Deceaſe of Sir <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> choſen Preſident of this Hoſpital, thought fit to accept of that Province: but upon view of it, he took notice that it was greatly gone to Ruin, the Ground about the Lodgings in a long tract of time rais'd ſo high, that the Patients lay as it were in a Cellar, without the benefit of Air or good Scent, but cloſe and noiſom: And the Roof and Walls ſo out of Repair, that the poor Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients oft-times could not lie dry in their Beds. He ſaw the greater part of it muſt be Rebuilt, it could not be Repair'd; and that the Rebuilding could not be delay'd without great Danger and Damage to the place, whereof ſome part prevented the Workmens pulling it down, by falling of it ſelf: Therefore, knowing well his Friend Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Activity, and good Addreſs in Works of that nature, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to be choſen one of the Governours of that Hoſpital. He was choſe in <hi>April;</hi> and finding that the Revenues of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital would go but a little way in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buildings or Repairs, and beſides could not be well ſpared from the Supply of the Wounded and Sick; in <hi>July</hi> he got him three round Boxes, in each of them a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97235:37"/>Parchment, one for Subſcriptions of 100 <hi>l.</hi> the ſecond for Subſcriptions of 50 <hi>l.</hi> the third for 25 or 20 Pound Subſcriptions. The Preſident was pleaſed to ſubſcribe 300 <hi>l.</hi> and other Governours were liberal; ſo were divers Merchants, and other rich Traders; that the whole Subſcription was not much ſhort of Four thouſand Pounds. Without doubt, the moſt of this Mony would have been ſubſcribed, tho' Mr. <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> had not been the Solicitor for it: yet I reckon, and am ſupported in my compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation by knowing and equal Judges, that the Subſcription was greater by a Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds, than it would have been if Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> had not been concerned in procuring and improving the Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. A proſpect of the Charge being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and ſome Mony (near 4000 <hi>l.</hi>) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward it procured; Materials muſt alſo be provided; and Workmen conſulted and agreed with. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> was conſtant in the Committee appointed for that matter: I took notice, that the Maſter-Builders made their moſt frequent application to him; and he was as careful to overſee their Proceedings. Several of the Wards for the Patients are now finiſht; beſides a ſpacious Hall, ſupported by Pillars, which make a very handſom Piazza. It trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97235:37"/>the Governours very much, that they were obliged to rebuild the Church of that Pariſh, which would coſt ſome Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Pounds, that could not be taken out of the revenue of the Hoſpital, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great prejudice to the Houſe and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents. It happen'd that the Parliament were then about ſettling a Tax for finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church in <hi>London;</hi> ſo the Governours of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> Hoſpital petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> to have ſome ſhare in that Tax toward the Rebuilding their Church: but becauſe many other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes prayed the like aſſiſtance at the ſame time, the Houſe, upon a debate in a Grand Committee, reſolved, that only St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s and <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Abby Churches ſhould have any ſuch proviſion allowed to them. Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> hereupon came home, not a little heavy: but he, and another of the Governours, put into Writing (that very night) ſome reaſons, why St. <hi>Thomas</hi> his Church might better claim ſome favour of the Honourable Houſe, than other ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Churches. They uſed ſuch diligence as to get their Paper printed againſt the next morning: Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> and his Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate gave copies of it to the Members as they entered the Houſe; telling them, they muſt not expect to have any ſick or
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97235:38"/>wounded Seamen cur'd, if they did not grant ſomething towards the Rebuilding of that Church: The effect was, that the Houſe took the matter again into conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and allowed 3000 <hi>l.</hi> to the Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal for the uſe deſired: On which our Friend came home with more pleaſure and ſatisfaction, than if an Eſtate of that value had fallen to himſelf.</p>
            <p>Among his other Charities, he was not unmindful of thoſe that ſuffered by Fire, but would immediately apply himſelf to 'em for their preſent Relief: afterwards he aſſiſted 'em in ſoliciting their Briefs, and to manage their Briefs (when obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) to the beſt advantage. He often lent mony to honeſt perſons, to anſwer ſudden emergences or diſtreſſes; but he loſt ſo much this way, that he was forced at laſt, reſolutely to forbear lending: but, inſtead of lending, he would many times give ſome part of what they deſired to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</p>
            <p>He put very many Boys to Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and contributed to ſetting them up, if they had ſerved their Apprentiſhips faithfully and diligently. He has told me that the Clergy of <hi>London,</hi> and other dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified Perſons in the Church, often ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him in this kind of Charity: He
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97235:38"/>ſaid, he had put many Boys out with the mony of ſome of the richer Clergy; who conſidered this (he thought) as a ſort of Charity that extends to the perſon's whole life, and might be the ground of many Charities in time to come.</p>
            <p>It deſerves, in my opinion, to be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among his Charities, that when (ſome two or three years ſince) there was a great Scarcity of current Coin, all the mony in <hi>England</hi> being either clipp'd, or debas'd by mixture of coarſe metals; he leſſened his expence by laying down his Coach, that he might be the more able to continue his former Charities, at a time when they were more needful than ever.</p>
            <p>I have now accounted for the general Endeavours and Performances of Mr. <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi>'s Life: the particulars, to each gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Head, were too numerous to be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, without tiring the Reader, if not alſo the Writer. But we have taken, tho' but a ſhort, view of a Perſon, of middle Extraction and ſlender Beginnings, who raiſed himſelf to the honor of a very great number of Illuſtrious Friendſhips, and to an affluence of Worldly Wealth. To which when he had attained, by Induſtry, Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, and Worth, like our Saviour, <hi>He
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:97235:39"/>went about doing good.</hi> Nay, like the ſame our Saviour, <hi>He became Poor, that through his Poverty others might be Rich.</hi> A Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who in reſpect of his endeavours <hi>in all kinds</hi> of Charity, may deſervedly be called <hi>the Father of the Poor;</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Reſugees, <hi>the Almoner of</hi> England. The Divine Hand had qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified him to do much Good; himſelf ſought out the Objects and Occaſions for it, and delighted in the doing. He did it with ſo much diligence and application, that he might even have ſaid, with our Saviour, <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me; and to finiſh his Works,</hi> i. e. the Works that he hath commanded. <hi>John</hi> 4.34.</p>
            <p>The Jeſuit that aſſiſted the late famous Marſhal <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> in his laſt hours, thought he might put this queſtion to him: Well, Sir, tell me, had you not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther now to have given one Alms to a poor Man, in his diſtreſs, for God's ſake, than to have won ſo many Victories in the Field of Battel? The Marſhal confeſs'd he ſhould now chooſe the former; ſeeing nothing will avail any man, in the Eternal World, but only the Actions of Charity; or of Juſtice and Piety. The Confeſſor doth not ſeem to have been impertinent in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97235:39"/>the queſtion; for in our ſerious laſt hours, we ſhall all be ſenſible, and forward to confeſs, that we were Wiſe only in that part of our life, that was laid out in the duties either of Humanity to Men, or Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety to God. The <hi>Craſſi</hi> and <hi>Craeſi,</hi> the <hi>Hannibals</hi> and <hi>Luxemburghs,</hi> the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous for Wealth, or Military Glory, how gladly would they now give all that Tinſel, for ſome part of our <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Sweat and Drudgeries for the Poor, and for the Deſerving? Is it for want of FAITH, or of CONSIDERATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON, that we ſo much more delight to read the Acts of the <hi>Alexanders,</hi> the <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemains,</hi> and other falſe Heroes, than of Perſons that have been exemplary for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Beneficence, or Devotion; and are now Triumphant in Heaven, on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of thoſe Services to God, and to Men? But ſo it is, either becauſe we <hi>are not Chriſtians,</hi> or becauſe we <hi>are Fools;</hi> we are (commonly ſpeaking) better plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the Sons of Earth, than of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>I have read ſomewhere, but ſo long ſince, that I forget the Author's Name, and the Subject of his Book; that the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of <hi>Judas,</hi> who betray'd our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, is, that he ſtands on the ſurface of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97235:40"/>a ſwelling dreadful Sea, with his Feet ſomewhat below the water, as if he were about to ſink. The Writer ſaith, beſides his continual horror and fear of going to the bottom, a moſt terrible Tempeſt of Hail and Wind always beats on the Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors naked body and head: he ſuffers as much by Cold, and the ſmart of the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Hail, as 'tis poſſible to imagine, that he could ſuffer by the Fire of Purgatory, or of Hell. But, ſaith my Author further, in this ſo great diſtreſs, <hi>Judas</hi> has one very great Comfort and Relief; for whereas the Tempeſt would be importable, if it beat always upon him from all ſides; at a little diſtance from him, and ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove him, there is ſtretched out a ſheet of ſtrong coarſe Linen-cloth; which ſheet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepts a great part of the Tempeſt. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> regales himſelf by turning ſometimes one ſide, ſometimes another ſide of his head and body, to the ſhelter of this ſheet. In ſhort, the ſheet is ſuch a Protection to him, that it defends him from the one half of his Puniſhment. But by what merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Action, or Actions, did <hi>Judas</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſo great a Favour? Our Author an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, He gave juſt the ſame quantity of Linen-cloth to a certain poor Family, for Shirting. It had been impoſſible that this
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97235:40"/>Gentleman ſhould hit on ſuch a conceit as this; but from <hi>our Natural Opinion</hi> of the value and merit of Charity; it ſeems to us a Virtue ſo Excellent, that it may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe even <hi>Judas</hi> from ſome part of his Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. I can hardly afford to ask the Reader's pardon for this Tale; I incline to think, that divers others may be as well pleaſed with the Wit of it, and the Moral implyed in it, as I have been, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it after above 40 years reading, without remembring either the Author, or Argument of the Book.</p>
            <p>I return once more to our dear <hi>Firmin,</hi> to take leave of him forever. He had ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much weakned his (otherwiſe) ſtrong and firm Conſtitution, by his manifold Charitable Imployments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> having been ſometimes liable to <hi>Jaundies,</hi> often affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with <hi>Colicks,</hi> and ſcarce ever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Cough;</hi> his Lungs had long been Pty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical. He would often return home ſo tired and depreſſed in his Spirits, that his Pulſe was ſcarce to be felt, or very lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guid: he would then take a little reſt in his Chair, and ſtart up out of it, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear very vigorous in Company, eſpecially where any good was to be done. The more immediate cauſe of his death was a Fever which ſeiz'd his Spirits, beginning
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97235:41"/>with a chilneſs and ſhivering, and then a heat enſued. He was at the ſame time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted both in his Lungs with a great ſhortneſs of breath, not having ſtrength to expectorate, and alſo with ſuch terrible pains in his Bowels, that for many hours nothing could be made to paſs him. He had for many years been troubled with a large Rupture. All which made his Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs very ſhort. He had wiſht in his life-time, that he might not lie above two days on his laſt Sick-bed; God granted to him his deſire; he lay not ſo long by eight hours: And <hi>Decemb.</hi> 20. about two of the Clock in the morning, <hi>Anno</hi> 1697. he died.</p>
            <p>During his decumbiture, he was viſited by his moſt dear Friend the Biſhop of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter:</hi> What paſſed between em his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hath made me to know, under his own hand, in theſe words. <hi>Mr.</hi> Firmin <hi>told me he was now going: and I truſt, ſaid he, God will not condemn me to worſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany than I have loved, and uſed, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Life. I replied, That he had been an extraordinary Example of Charity; the Poor had a wonderful Bleſſing in you: I doubt not, theſe works will follow you; if you have no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation from the merit of them; but rely on the infinite Goodneſs of God, and the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97235:41"/>of our Saviour. Here he anſwered,</hi> I do ſo: <hi>and I ſay, in the words of my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> When I have done all, I am but an unprofitable Servant. <hi>He was in ſuch an Agony of body, for want of breath, that I did not think fit to ſpeak more to him, but only give him aſſurance of my earneſt Prayers for him, while he remained in this World. Then I took ſolemn and affectionate farewel of him; and he of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is uſual to conclude Lives with a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Perſons, both as to their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and the qualities of their Minds: Therefore I muſt further add. Mr. <hi>Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> was of a lower Stature, well proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned; his Complexion fair and bright; his Eye and Countenance lively; his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect manly, and promiſing ſomewhat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary; you would readily take him for a Man of good Senſe, Worth, and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Walking or Sitting he appeared more comely than ſtanding ſtill; for his Mein and Action gave a gracefulneſs to his Perſon.</p>
            <p>The endowments, inclinations, and qualities of his Mind, may be beſt judged by the account we have given of his Life. It appears, he was quick of apprehenſion, and diſpatch, and yet almoſt indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97235:42"/>Induſtrious; properties that very rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meet in the ſame Man. He was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, Inquiſitive and very Ingenious; that is, he had a thirſt of knowing much; and his fine and mercurial Wit enabled him to acquire a large Knowledg, with little la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, but he was utterly againſt ſubtilties in Religion. He could not diſſemble; on the contrary, you might eaſily perceive his love or anger, his liking or diſlike: methoughts, in both theſe reſpects he was rather too open; but both are the effects of ſincerity, and arguments of an honeſt mind. He never affected proudly the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of others, whether above or below him: with which I was the better ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, becauſe it follows, that his Charities proceeded not from any affectation of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or Glory among Men; but from the love of God and his afflicted Brother. He was Facetious enough, but without af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting it; for he valued (what indeed himſelf excelled in) Judgment, rather than Wit. He was neither preſuming or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bold, nor yet timorous; a little prone to Anger, but never exceſſive in it, either as to meaſure or time: which Acraſies, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you ſay of the Body or Mind, occaſion great Uneaſineſs, and ſometimes great Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities and Miſchiefs, to Perſons who
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97235:42"/>are ridden by thoſe Paſſions. If the mind is turbulent by ſtrong Paſſions of any ſort, the life is ſeldom ſerene and calm; but vexed with great Griefs and Miſadven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. His manner of Converſing was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable; ſo that ſeldom any broke friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with him. Being well aſſured in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of his own Integrity, he could even unconcernedly hear that this or that Man ſpoke ill of him. When I told him of that infamous Story of the impudent Coffee-Man, which had been broached 6 or 7 years before, had he not been over perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he would not have taken any notice of him: Yet was more concern'd at Mr. <hi>B's</hi> printing it, than at the other fellow's inventing it; not from the leaſt conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of guilt, but that he ſhould be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianly us'd by a Miniſter of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, who too raſhly took up the Story a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. Which ſhews what ſtrange things may be done under pretence of a Zeal for Religion.</p>
            <p>My Lady <hi>Clayton</hi> has ſo great a Reſpect for his Memory, that ſhe has (with the concurrence of Sir <hi>Robert</hi>) ſince his death, erected a handſom Monument in their Garden at <hi>Marden</hi> in <hi>Surry,</hi> in a Walk <hi>there,</hi> called <hi>Mr. Firmin's Walk,</hi> by reaſon of his Contrivance and Activity in it. This
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97235:43"/>Monument is a Marble-pillar, about eight foot high, with an Urn, and Flowers growing out of the top of it, with this Motto, <hi>Floreſcit funere virtus,</hi> an Emblem you may conceive of Death and Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. There is alſo a Marble-table fix'd to one ſide of this Pillar, with the Inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on following.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="inscription">
               <body>
                  <head>To perpetuate (as far as Marble and Love can do it) the Memory of <hi>Thomas Firmin,</hi> Citizen of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>NONE ever paſs'd the ſeveral periods of Human Life more irreprochably, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd the common Duties of Society with greater Sincerity and Approbation. Though it appears, by his public Spirit, that he thought himſelf born rather for the Benefit of others, than his own private Advantage; yet the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of doing Good, and the univerſal Eſteem of honeſt men, made him the happieſt Perſon in the World. But his Charity (which was not confin'd to any Nation, Sect, or Party) is moſt worthy thy Imitation, at leaſt in ſome degree, O Reader. He was as Liberal of his own, as Faithful in Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the pious Donations of others, whom he ſuccesfully perſuaded to relieve the diſtreſſed,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:97235:43"/>particularly the laborious Poor; for of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant, idle, and inſolent Beggers, he was no Advocate nor Encourager. His agreeable Temper rendring him an extraordinary lover of Gardens, he contriv'd this Walk, which bears his Name, and where his improving Converſation and Example are ſtill remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred. But ſince Heaven has better diſpoſed of him, this Pillar is erected to Charity and Friendſhip by Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> and <hi>Martha</hi> his Lady, who firſt builded and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>Marden.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Born at <hi>Ipſwich,</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Buried in <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> Hoſpital, <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I have now anſwer'd the Demand of divers, as well Strangers as Friends, of writing and publiſhing ſome account of Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi>'s Life and Death: I hope the well-minded Reader will find much in it, that may both confirm and ſtrengthen him in the beſt Ways, eſpecially in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity and Charity. He may ſee here, how much beneficence a good Man, of but indifferent Eſtate, is capable of exerciſing, by means of Acquaintance and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with well-choſe Friends; whom he may excite, by his Example and Solicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97235:44"/>to be highly uſeful in their Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and thereby, be himſelf incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly more uſeful, than otherwiſe he could be. But if I am leſs ſuccesful in that part of my Deſign, than I wiſh to be; yet I have much eaſed my own mind, by pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome part of the debt that I owe to the Memory of our Friend. The reſt I ſhall be always paying, by a Grateful and Mournful Senſe of the <hi>Public</hi> and my <hi>own</hi> Loſs and Benefit by him, when pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and as now deceaſed.</p>
            <p>I cannot better end than in the words of a Letter, written to the Author of the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Sermon, by a Perſon of great Worth; and who, from the time that they came acquainted, enabled Mr. <hi>Firmin</hi> to do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe great Services to the Public, the Deſerving, and the Poor, for which he was ſo highly commendable.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Sir, I received your Letter of <hi>Febr.</hi> 16. and therewith the Parentation to our valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Friend Mr. <hi>Tho. Firmin;</hi> that Man, of ſo extraordinary Affections, and Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, for the great Works of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Piety.</hi> May it pleaſe the Divine <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, to raiſe up to us adequate Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</hi> In the mean time, what <hi>an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batement of ſorrow</hi> is it to us, that <hi>He, who alone is Abſolutely good, and All-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:97235:44"/>lives forever?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>— I am your aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ctionate and aſſured Friend, <hi>Br. Br.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>He had often ſignified his deſire to be buried in <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> Hoſpital, when dead, the Care of which had been ſo much upon his heart while living. In compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with which deſire, his Relatives have interr'd him in the Cloyſters there; and placed in the Wall adjoining a Marble to his memory, with this Inſcription, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder that Stone, near this place, lyeth the Body of <hi>Thomas Firmin,</hi> late Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> a Governour of this and Saint <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Hoſpital; who, by the Grace of God, was created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good Works, wherein he was indefatigably Induſtrious, and ſuccesfully provoked many others thereto; becoming alſo their Almo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, viſiting and relieving the Poor at their Houſes; and in Priſons, whence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he redeemed many. He ſet many Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of them at work, to the expending of great Stocks: He rebuilt, repaired, and added Conveniences to Hoſpitals, weekly over-ſeeing the Orphans. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugees from <hi>France,</hi> and from <hi>Ireland,</hi> have partaken largely the effects of his Charity, Pains, and earneſt Solicitations for them. He was wonderfully Zealous in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:97235:45"/>every good Work, beyond the Example of any in our Age. Thus ſhewed he his Faith by his Works, and cannot reaſonably be reproched for that which brought forth ſuch plenty of Good Fruits.</p>
                  <p>He Died <hi>Dec. xx. 1697.</hi> and in the <hi>66th</hi> year of his Age.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <trailer>The End of the Life.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97235:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
